<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter id="existing-setup">
  <chapterinfo>
    <mediaobject condition="pdf">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/chap-existant.png" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Existing Setup</keyword>
      <keyword>Reuse</keyword>
      <keyword>Migration</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>Analyzing the Existing Setup and Migrating</title>
  <highlights>
    <para>Any computer system overhaul should take the existing system into
    account. This allows reuse of available resources as much as possible
    and guarantees interoperability of the various elements comprising the
    system. This study will introduce a generic framework to follow in any
    migration of a computing infrastructure to Linux.</para>
  </highlights>
  <section id="sect.heterogeneous-environments">
    <title>Coexistence in Heterogeneous Environments</title>
    <indexterm><primary>environment</primary><secondary>heterogeneous environment</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>Debian integrates very well in all types of existing environments
    and plays well with any other operating system. This near-perfect
    harmony comes from market pressure which demands that software
    publishers develop programs that follow standards. Compliance with
    standards allow administrators to switch out programs: clients or
    servers, whether free or not.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Integration with Windows Machines</title>

      <para>Samba's SMB/CIFS support ensures excellent communication within
      a Windows context. It shares files and print queues to Windows
      clients and includes software that allow a Linux machine to use
      resources available on Windows servers.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>TOOL</emphasis> Samba</title>
        <indexterm><primary>Samba</primary></indexterm>

	<para>Samba version 2 behaves like a Windows NT server
	(authentication, files, print queues, downloading printer drivers,
	DFS, etc.) Version 3 works with Active Directory, brings
	interoperability with NT4 domain controllers, and supports RPCs
	(Remote Procedure Calls). Version 4 is a rewrite (still
	experimental), the purpose of which is to provide functionality of
	a domain controller compatible with Active Directory.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Integration with Mac OS machines</title>

      <para>Netatalk is a program which uses the Appletalk protocol
      (running on a Linux kernel) and allows Debian to interface with a Mac
      OS network. It ensures the operation of the file server and print
      queues, as well as time server (clock synchronization). Its router
      function allows interconnection with Appletalk networks.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Integration with Other Linux/Unix Machines</title>

      <para>Finally, NFS and NIS, both included, guarantee interaction with
      Unix systems. NFS ensures file server functionality, while NIS
      creates user directories. The BSD printing layer, used by most Unix
      systems, also allows sharing of print queues.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Coexistence of Debian with MacOS, Windows and Unix systems</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/existant-1.png" width="25%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.how-to-migrate">
    <title>How To Migrate</title>
    <indexterm><primary>migration</primary></indexterm>

    <para>In order to guarantee continuity of the services, each computer
    migration must be planned and executed according to the plan. Whatever
    the operating system used, this principle never changes.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Survey and Identify Services</title>

      <para>As simple as it seems, this step is essential. A serious
      administrator truly knows the principal roles of each server, but
      such roles can change, and sometimes experienced users may have
      installed “wild” services. Knowing that they exist will at least
      allow you to decide what to do with them, rather than delete them
      haphazardly.</para>

      <para>For this purpose, it is wise to inform your users of the
      project before migrating the server. To involve them in the project,
      it may be useful to install the most common free software programs on
      their desktops prior to migration, which they will come across again
      after the migration to Debian; OpenOffice.org and the Mozilla suite
      are the best examples here.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Network and Processes</title>

       
	<para><indexterm><primary><command>nmap</command></primary></indexterm>
	The <command>nmap</command> tool (in the package with the same
	name) will quickly identify Internet services hosted by a network
	connected machine without even requiring to log in to it. Simply
	call the following command on another machine connected to the same
	network:</para>

        <screen>
<computeroutput>$ </computeroutput><userinput>nmap mirlaine</userinput>
<computeroutput>Starting Nmap 5.00 ( http://nmap.org ) at 2010-07-29 16:36 CET
Interesting ports on mirlaine (192.168.1.99):
Not shown: 1694 closed ports
PORT    STATE SERVICE
22/tcp  open  ssh
79/tcp  open  finger
111/tcp open  rpcbind

Nmap done: 1 IP address (1 host up) scanned in 0.19 seconds</computeroutput>
</screen>

        <sidebar>
          <title><emphasis>ALTERNATIVE</emphasis> Use <command>netstat</command> to find the list of available services</title>

	  <para>On a Linux machine, the <command>netstat -tupan</command>
	  command will show the list of active or pending TCP sessions, as
	  well UDP ports on which running programs are listening. This
	  facilitates identification of services offered on the
	  network.</para>
        </sidebar>

        <sidebar>
          <title><emphasis>GOING FURTHER</emphasis> IPv6</title>

	  <para>Some network commands may work either with IPv4 (the
	  default usually) or with IPv6. This is especially the case with
	  the <command>nmap</command> and <command>netstat</command>
	  commands, but also others, such as <command>route</command> or
	  <command>ip</command>. The convention is that this behavior is
	  enabled by the <parameter>-6</parameter> command-line
	  option.</para>
        </sidebar>

	<para>If the server is a Unix machine offering shell accounts to
	users, it is interesting to determine if processes are executed in
	the background in the absence of their owner. The command
	<command>ps auxw</command> displays a list of all processes with
	their user identity. By checking this information against the
	output of the <command>who</command> command, which gives a list of
	logged in users, it is possible to identify wild servers or
	programs running in the background. Looking at
	<filename>crontabs</filename> (tables listing automatic actions
	scheduled by users) will often provide interesting information on
	functions fulfilled by the server (a complete explanation of
	<command>cron</command> is available in <xref
	linkend="sect.task-scheduling-cron-atd"/>).</para>

	<para>In any case, it is essential to backup your servers: this
	allows recovery of information after the fact, when users will
	report specific problems due to the migration.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Backing up the Configuration</title>

      <para>It is wise to retain the configuration of every service
      identified in order to be able to install the equivalent on the
      updated server. The strict minimum is to print the configuration
      files and make a backup copy of them.</para>

      <para>For Unix machines, the configuration files are usually found in
      <filename>/etc/</filename>, but they may be located in a
      sub-directory of <filename>/usr/local/</filename>. This is the case
      if a program has been installed from sources, rather than with a
      package. One may also find them, in some cases, under
      <filename>/opt/</filename>.</para>

      <para>For data managing services (such as databases), it is strongly
      recommended to export them to a standard format that will be easily
      imported by the new software. Such a format is usually in text mode
      and documented; it may be, for example, an SQL dump for a database,
      or an LDIF file for an LDAP server.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Database backups</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/existant-2.png" width="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Each server software is different, and it is impossible to
      detail all existing cases. See the new and current software
      documentation to identify the exportable (thus, re-importable)
      portions and those which will require manual manipulation. Reading
      this book will clarify the configuration of the main Linux server
      programs.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Taking Over an Existing Debian Server</title>
      <indexterm><primary>recovering a Debian machine</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>exploring a Debian machine</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>taking over a Debian server</primary></indexterm>

      <para>To effectively take over its maintenance, one may analyze a
      machine already running with Debian.</para>

      <para>The first file to check is
      <filename>/etc/debian_version</filename>, which usually contains the
      version number for the installed Debian system (it is part of the
      <emphasis>base-files</emphasis> package). If it indicates
      <literal><replaceable>codename</replaceable>/sid</literal>, it means
      that the system was updated with packages coming from one of the
      development distributions (either testing or unstable).</para>

      <para>The <command>apt-show-versions</command> program (from the
      Debian package of the same name) checks the list of packages
      installed and identifies the versions available.
      <command>aptitude</command> can also be used for these tasks, albeit
      in a less systematic manner.</para>

      <para>A glance at the <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> file
      will show where the installed Debian packages likely came from. If
      many unknown sources appear, the administrator may choose to
      completely reinstall the computer's system to ensure optimal
      compatibility with the software provided by Debian.</para>

      <para>The <filename>sources.list</filename> file is often a good
      indicator: the majority of administrators keep, at least in comments,
      the list of prior APT sources used. But you should not forget that
      sources used in the past might have been deleted, and that some
      random packages grabbed on the Internet might have been manually
      installed (with the <command>dpkg</command> command). In this case,
      the machine is misleading in its appearance of “standard” Debian.
      This is why you should pay attention to any indication that will give
      away the presence of external packages (appearance of
      <filename>deb</filename> files in unusual directories, package
      version numbers with a special suffix indicating that it originated
      from outside the Debian project, such as <literal>ubuntu</literal> or
      <literal>ximian</literal>, etc.)</para>

      <para>Likewise, it is interesting to analyze the contents of the
      directory <filename>/usr/local/</filename>, intended to contain
      programs compiled and installed manually. Listing software installed
      in this manner is instructive, since this raises questions on the
      reasons for not using the corresponding Debian package, if such a
      package exists.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>QUICK LOOK</emphasis> <emphasis role="pkg">cruft</emphasis></title>

	<para>The <emphasis role="pkg">cruft</emphasis> package proposes to
	list the available files that are not owned by any package. It has
	some filters (more or less effective, and more or less up to date)
	to avoid reporting some legitimate files (files generated by Debian
	packages, or generated configuration files not managed by
	<command>dpkg</command>, etc.).</para>

	<para>Be careful to not blindly delete everything that
	<command>cruft</command> might list!</para>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Installing Debian</title>

      <para>All information on the current server being now known, we can
      shut it down and begin to install Debian on it.</para>
      <indexterm><primary>architecture</primary></indexterm>

      <para>To choose the appropriate version, we must know the computer's
      architecture. If it is a PC, it is most likely to be i386. In other
      cases, we can narrow down the possibilities according to the
      previously used system.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Installing the appropriate Debian version</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/existant-3.png" width="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><xref linkend="tab-corresp" xrefstyle="nopage"/> is not
      intended to be exhaustive, but may be helpful. In any case, the
      original documentation for the computer is the most reliable source
      to find this information.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>HARDWARE</emphasis> Next-generation PC</title>
        <indexterm><primary>Itanium</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>amd64</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>ia64</primary></indexterm>

	<para>Most recent computers have 64 bit Intel or AMD processors,
	compatible with older 32 bit processors; the software compiled for
	“i386” architecture thus works. On the other hand, this
	compatibility mode does not fully exploit the capabilities of these
	new processors. This is why Debian provides software for “ia64”
	architecture for Intel Itanium chips and “amd64” for AMD chips.
	This last also works with Intel “em64t” processors, which are
	very similar to AMD64 processors.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <table colsep="1" id="tab-corresp">
        <title>Matching operating system and architecture</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Operating System</entry>
              <entry>Architecture(s)</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>DEC Unix (OSF/1)</entry>
              <entry>alpha, mipsel</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>HP Unix</entry>
              <entry>hppa</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>IBM AIX</entry>
              <entry>powerpc</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Irix</entry>
              <entry>mips</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>MacOS</entry>
              <entry>powerpc, m68k, i386, amd64</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>MVS</entry>
              <entry>s390</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Solaris, SunOS</entry>
              <entry>sparc, m68k, i386</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Ultrix</entry>
              <entry>mips</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>VMS</entry>
              <entry>alpha</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Windows NT</entry>
              <entry>i386, alpha, mipsel</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Windows XP / Windows Server 2008</entry>
              <entry>i386, ia64, amd64</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Windows Vista / Windows 7</entry>
              <entry>i386, amd64</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Installing and Configuring the Selected Services</title>

      <para>Once Debian is installed, we must install and configure one by
      one all of the services that this computer must host. The new
      configuration must take into consideration the prior one in order to
      ensure a smooth transition. All the information collected in the
      first two steps are useful to successfully complete this part.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Install the selected services</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/existant-4.png" width="66%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Prior to jumping in to this exercise with both feet, it is
      strongly recommended that you read the remainder of this book. After
      that you will have a more precise understanding of how to configure
      the expected services.</para>

      <para/>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
