<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter id="apt">
  <chapterinfo>
    <mediaobject condition="pdf">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/chap-apt.png" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>apt-get</keyword>
      <keyword>apt-cache</keyword>
      <keyword>aptitude</keyword>
      <keyword>synaptic</keyword>
      <keyword>sources.list</keyword>
      <keyword>apt-cdrom</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title>Maintenance and Updates: The APT Tools</title>
  <highlights>
    <para>What makes Debian so popular with administrators is how easily
    software can be installed and how easily the whole system can be
    updated. This unique advantage is largely due to the
    <emphasis>APT</emphasis> program, that Falcot Corp
    administrators studied with enthusiasm.</para>
  </highlights>

  <para><indexterm><primary>APT</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>Advanced Package Tool</primary></indexterm> APT is
  the abbreviation for Advanced Package Tool. What makes this program
  “advanced” is its approach to packages. It doesn't simply evaluate
  them individually, but it considers them as a whole and produces the best
  possible combination of packages depending on what is available and
  compatible (according to dependencies).</para>

  <sidebar>
    <title><emphasis>VOCABULARY</emphasis> Package source and source package</title>

    <para>The word <emphasis>source</emphasis> can be ambiguous. A source
    package — a package containing the source code of a program —
    should not be confused with a package source — a repository (website,
    FTP server, CD-ROM, local directory, etc.) which contains
    packages.</para>
  </sidebar>

  <para>APT needs to be given a “list of package sources”: the file
  <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> will list the different
  repositories (or “sources”) that publish Debian packages. APT will
  then import the list of packages published by each of these sources. This
  operation is achieved by downloading <filename>Packages.{gz,bz2,lzma,xz}</filename>
  files (in case of a source of binary packages) and
  <filename>Sources.{gz,bz2,lzma,xz}</filename> (in case of a source of source
  packages) and by analyzing their contents. When an old copy of these
  files is already present, APT can update it by only downloading the
  differences (see sidebar <xref linkend="sidebar.apt-pdiff"/>).</para>
  <indexterm><primary><filename>Packages.gz</filename></primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary><filename>Sources.gz</filename></primary></indexterm>

  <sidebar>
    <title><emphasis>BACK TO BASICS</emphasis> <command>gzip</command>, <command>bzip2</command>, <command>LZMA</command> and <command>XZ</command> Compression</title>
    <indexterm><primary><command>gzip</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>bzip2</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>lzma</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>xz</command></primary></indexterm>

    <para>A <filename>.gz</filename> extension refers to a file
    compressed with the <command>gzip</command>
    utility. <command>gzip</command> is the fast and efficient
    traditional Unix utility to compress files.  Newer tools achieve
    better rates of compression but require more resources
    (computation time and memory) to compress and uncompress a
    file. Among them, and by order of appearance, there are
    <command>bzip2</command> (generating files with a
    <filename>.bz2</filename> extension), <command>lzma</command>
    (generating <filename>.lzma</filename> files) and
    <command>xz</command> (generating <filename>.xz</filename>
    files).</para>
  </sidebar>
  <section id="sect.apt-sources.list">
    <title>Filling in the <filename>sources.list</filename> File</title>
    <indexterm><primary><filename>sources.list</filename></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>source</primary><secondary>of packages</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>package</primary><secondary>source of</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename></primary></indexterm>

    <section>
      <title>Syntax</title>

      <para>Each active line of the
      <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> file contains the
      description of a source, made of 3 parts separated by spaces.</para>

      <para>The first field indicates the source type:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>“<literal>deb</literal>” for binary packages,</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>“<literal>deb-src</literal>” for source packages.</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The second field gives the base URL of the source (combined with
      the filenames present in the <filename>Packages.gz</filename> files, it
      must give a full and valid URL): this can consist in a Debian mirror or
      in any other package archive set up by a third party. The URL can start
      with <literal>file://</literal> to indicate a local source installed in
      the system's file hierarchy, with <literal>http://</literal> to
      indicate a source accessible from a web server, or with
      <literal>ftp://</literal> for a source available on an FTP server. The
      URL can also start with <literal>cdrom://</literal> for CD-ROM/DVD-ROM/Blu-ray 
      disc based installations, although this is less frequent, since
      network-based installation methods are more and more common.</para>

      <para>The syntax of the last field depends on the structure of the
      repository. In the simplest cases, you can simply indicate a
      subdirectory (with a required trailing slash) of the desired source
      (this is often a simple “<filename>./</filename>” which refers to the
      absence of a subdirectory — the packages are then directly at the
      specified URL). But in the most common case, the repositories will be
      structured like a Debian mirror, with multiple distributions each
      having multiple components. In those cases, name the chosen
      distribution (by its “codename” — see the list in sidebar <xref
      linkend="sidebar.bruce-perens"/> — or by the corresponding “suites” —
      <literal>stable</literal>, <literal>testing</literal>,
      <literal>unstable</literal>), then the components (or sections) to
      enable (chosen between <literal>main</literal>,
      <literal>contrib</literal>, and <literal>non-free</literal> in a
      typical Debian mirror).</para>

      <sidebar id="sidebar.sections" role="important">
	<title><emphasis>VOCABULARY</emphasis> The <literal>main</literal>, <literal>contrib</literal> and <literal>non-free</literal> archives</title>
	<indexterm><primary>section</primary><secondary><literal>main</literal></secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary><literal>main</literal>, section</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>section</primary><secondary><literal>contrib</literal></secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary><literal>contrib</literal>, section</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>section</primary><secondary><literal>non-free</literal></secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary><literal>non-free</literal>, section</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>component (of a repository)</primary></indexterm>

	<para>Debian uses three sections to differentiate packages according
	to the licenses chosen by the authors of each work.
	<literal>Main</literal> gathers all
	packages which fully comply with the Debian Free Software
	Guidelines.</para>

	<para>The <literal>non-free</literal> archive is
	different because it contains software which does not (entirely)
	conform to these principles but which can nevertheless be distributed
	without restrictions. This archive, which is not officially part of Debian, is a
	service for users who could need some of those programs — however Debian
	always recommends giving priority to free software. The existence of
	this section represents a considerable problem for Richard M.
	Stallman and keeps the Free Software Foundation from recommending
	Debian to users.</para>

	<para><literal>Contrib</literal> (contributions) is a
	set of open source software which cannot function without some
	non-free elements. These elements can be software from the
	<literal>non-free</literal> section, or non-free files
	such as game ROMs, BIOS of consoles, etc.
	<literal>Contrib</literal> also includes free software
	whose compilation requires proprietary elements. This was initially
	the case for the OpenOffice.org office suite, which used to require a
	proprietary Java environment.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <sidebar>
	<title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list.d/*.list</filename> files</title>

	<para>If many package sources are referenced, it can be useful to
	split them in multiple files. Each part is then stored in
	<filename>/etc/apt/sources.list.d/<replaceable>filename</replaceable>.list</filename>
	(see sidebar <xref linkend="sidebar.directory.d"/>).</para>
      </sidebar>

      <indexterm><primary><command>apt-cdrom</command></primary></indexterm>
      <para>The <literal>cdrom</literal> entries describe the CD/DVD-ROMs
      you have. Contrary to other entries, a CD-ROM is not always available
      since it has to be inserted into the drive and since only one disc
      can be read at a time. For those reasons, these sources are managed in a slightly different
      way, and need to be added with the
      <command>apt-cdrom</command> program, usually executed with the
      <literal>add</literal> parameter. The latter will then request the disc
      to be inserted in the drive and will browse its contents looking for
      <filename>Packages</filename> files. It will use these files to update
      its database of available packages (this operation is usually done by the
      <command>apt-get update</command> command). From then on, APT can
      require the disc to be inserted if it needs one of its packages.</para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Repositories for <emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> Users</title>
      
      <para>Here is a standard <filename>sources.list</filename> for a system running
      the <emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> version of Debian:</para>

      <!-- MAY CHANGE: default codename -->
      <example id="example.stable-sources-list">
	<title><filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> file for users of Debian Stable</title>

	<programlisting># Security updates
deb http://security.debian.org/ wheezy/updates main contrib non-free
deb-src http://security.debian.org/ wheezy/updates main contrib non-free

## Debian mirror

# Base repository
deb http://ftp.debian.org/debian wheezy main contrib non-free
deb-src http://ftp.debian.org/debian wheezy main contrib non-free

# Stable updates
deb http://ftp.debian.org/debian wheezy-updates main contrib non-free
deb-src http://ftp.debian.org/debian wheezy-updates main contrib non-free

# Stable backports
deb http://ftp.debian.org/debian wheezy-backports main contrib non-free
deb-src http://ftp.debian.org/debian wheezy-backports main contrib non-free
  </programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>This file lists all sources of packages associated with the
      <emphasis role="distribution">Wheezy</emphasis> version of Debian
      (the current <emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> as of
      this writing). We opted to name “wheezy” explicitly instead of using
      the corresponding “stable“ alias (<literal>stable</literal>, <literal>stable-updates</literal>, <literal>stable-backports</literal>) because we don't want to have the underlying
      distribution changed outside of our control when the next stable release
      comes out.</para>

      <sidebar>
	<title><emphasis>QUICK LOOK</emphasis> <command>apt-spy</command></title>
	<indexterm><primary><command>apt-spy</command></primary></indexterm>

	<para>This software tests the download speed from several Debian
	mirrors and generates a <filename>sources.list</filename> file which
	points to the fastest mirror.</para>

	<para>The mirror selected during installation is generally suitable
	since its selection is based on the country. However, if the download
	is a little slow, or after a move, you can try running the
	application available in the <emphasis role="pkg">apt-spy</emphasis>
	package.</para>
      </sidebar>
     
      <para>Most packages will come from the “base repository” which
      contains all packages but is seldom updated (about once every 2
      months for a “point release”). The other repositories are
      partial (they do not contain all packages) and can host updates
      (packages with newer version) that APT might install. The following
      sections will explain the purpose and the rules governing each of
      those repositories.</para>

      <para>Note that when the desired version of a package is available
      on several repositories, the first one listed in the
      <filename>sources.list</filename> file will be used. For this
      reason, non-official sources are usually added at the end of the
      file.</para>

      <para>As a side note, most of what this section says about
      <emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> applies equally
      well to <emphasis role="distribution">Oldstable</emphasis> since
      the latter is just an older <emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis>
      that is maintained in parallel.</para>

      <section id="sect.security-updates">
        <title>Security Updates</title>
	<indexterm><primary><literal>security.debian.org</literal></primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>security updates</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>updates</primary><secondary>security updates</secondary></indexterm>

	<para>The security updates are not hosted on the usual network of
	Debian mirrors but on <literal>security.debian.org</literal> (on a
	small set of machines maintained by the <link linkend="dsa-team">Debian System
	Administrators</link>). This archive contains security updates (prepared
	by the Debian Security Team and/or by package maintainers) for the
	<emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> distribution.</para>

	<para>The server can also host security updates for <emphasis
	role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> but this doesn't happen very
	often since those updates tend to reach <emphasis
	role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> via the regular flow of
	updates coming from <emphasis
	role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="sect.stable-updates">
        <title>Stable Updates</title>
	<indexterm><primary>stable updates</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary><literal>stable-updates</literal></primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>updates</primary><secondary>stable updates</secondary></indexterm>

	<para>Stable updates are not security sensitive but are deemed
	important enough to be pushed to users before the next stable
	point release.</para>

	<para>This repository will typically contain fixes for critical
	bugs which could not be fixed before release or which have been
	introduced by subsequent updates. Depending on the urgency, it can
	also contain updates for packages that have to evolve over time…
	like <emphasis role="pkg">spamassassin</emphasis>'s spam detection
	rules, <emphasis role="pkg">clamav</emphasis>'s virus database, or
	the daylight-saving rules of all timezones (<emphasis
	role="pkg">tzdata</emphasis>).</para>

	<para>In practice, this repository is a subset of the
	<literal>proposed-updates</literal> repository, carefully selected
	by the Stable Release Managers.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="sect.proposed-updates">
        <title>Proposed Updates</title>
        <indexterm><primary><literal>proposed-updates</literal></primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary><literal>stable-proposed-updates</literal></primary></indexterm>

	<para>Once published, the <emphasis
	role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> distribution is only updated
	about once every 2 months. The <literal>proposed-updates</literal>
	repository is where the expected updates are prepared (under the
	supervision of the Stable Release Managers).</para>

	<para>The security and stable updates documented in the former
	sections are always included in this repository, but there is more
	too, because package maintainers also have the opportunity to fix
	important bugs that do not deserve an immediate release.</para>
	
	<para>Anyone can use this repository
	to test those updates before their official publication. The
	extract below uses the <literal>wheezy-proposed-updates</literal>
	alias which is both more explicit and more consistent since
	<literal>squeeze-proposed-updates</literal> also exists (for the
	<emphasis role="distribution">Oldstable</emphasis> updates):</para>

        <programlisting>deb http://ftp.debian.org/debian wheezy-proposed-updates main contrib non-free
</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section id="sect.backports">
        <title>Stable Backports</title>
        <indexterm><primary><literal>stable-backports</literal></primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>backport</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>updates</primary><secondary>backports</secondary></indexterm>

	<para>The <literal>stable-backports</literal> repository hosts
	“package backports”. The term refers to a package of some recent
	software which has been recompiled for an older distribution,
	generally for <emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis>.
	</para>

	<para>When the distribution
	becomes a little dated, numerous software projects have released
	new versions that are not integrated into the current <emphasis
	role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> (which is only modified to
	address the most critical problems, such as security problems).
	Since the <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> and
	<emphasis role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> distributions can
	be more risky, package maintainers sometimes offer recompilations of
	recent software applications for <emphasis
	role="distribution">Stable</emphasis>, which has the advantage to
	limit potential instability to a small number of chosen packages.
	<ulink type="block" url="http://backports.debian.org"/>
	</para>

	<!-- MAY CHANGE: no repository on backports.debian.org-->
	<para>The <literal>stable-backports</literal> repository is now
	available on the usual Debian mirrors. But backports for
	<emphasis role="distribution">Squeeze</emphasis> are still hosted
	on a dedicated server (<literal>backports.debian.org</literal>),
	and requires the following <filename>sources.list</filename> entry:
	</para>

        <indexterm><primary><literal>backports.debian.org</literal></primary></indexterm>
        <programlisting>deb http://backports.debian.org/debian-backports squeeze-backports main contrib non-free
</programlisting>

	<para>Backports from <literal>stable-backports</literal> are
	always created from packages available in <emphasis
	role="distribution">Testing</emphasis>. This ensures that all
	installed backports will be upgradable to the corresponding stable
	version once the next stable release of Debian is available.
	</para>

	<para>Even though this repository provides newer versions of
	packages, APT will not install them unless you give explicit
	instructions to do so (or unless you have already done so with a
	former version of the given backport): </para>

	<screen>
$ <userinput>sudo apt-get install <replaceable>package</replaceable>/wheezy-backports</userinput>
$ <userinput>sudo apt-get install -t wheezy-backports <replaceable>package</replaceable></userinput>
	</screen>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Repositories for <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis>/<emphasis role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> Users</title>

      <para>Here is a standard <filename>sources.list</filename> for a
      system running the <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis>
      or <emphasis role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> version of
      Debian:</para>

      <example id="example.testing-sources-list">
	<title><filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> file for users of Debian
	<emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis>/<emphasis role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis></title>

	<programlisting>
# Unstable
deb http://ftp.debian.org/debian unstable main contrib non-free
deb-src http://ftp.debian.org/debian unstable main contrib non-free

# Testing
deb http://ftp.debian.org/debian testing main contrib non-free
deb-src http://ftp.debian.org/debian testing main contrib non-free

# Stable
deb http://ftp.debian.org/debian stable main contrib non-free
deb-src http://ftp.debian.org/debian stable main contrib non-free

# Security updates
deb http://security.debian.org/ stable/updates main contrib non-free
deb http://security.debian.org/ testing/updates main contrib non-free
deb-src http://security.debian.org/ stable/updates main contrib non-free
deb-src http://security.debian.org/ testing/updates main contrib non-free
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <para>With this <filename>sources.list</filename> file APT will
      install packages from <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>.  If that is not desired,
      use the <literal>APT::Default-Release</literal> setting (see <xref
      linkend="sect.apt-upgrade" />) to instruct APT to pick
      packages from another distribution (most likely <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> in this case).</para>

      <para>There are good reasons to include all those repositories, even
      though a single one should be enough. <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> users will appreciate the
      possibility to cherry-pick a fixed package from <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> when the version in
      <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> is affected by an
      annoying bug. On the opposite, <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> users bitten by unexpected
      regressions have the possibility to downgrade packages to their
      (supposedly working) <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> version.</para>

      <para>The inclusion of <emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis>
      is more debatable but it often gives access to some packages which
      have been removed from the development versions. It also ensures that
      you get the latest updates for packages which have not been modified
      since the last stable release.</para>

      <section>
        <title>The <emphasis role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis> Repository</title>
        <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis></primary></indexterm>

	<para>The archive of <emphasis
	role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis> packages is present on
	all Debian mirrors, and contains packages which are not in the
	<emphasis role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> version yet
	because of their substandard quality — they are often software
	development versions or pre-versions (alpha, beta, release
	candidate…). A package can also be sent there after undergoing
	subsequent changes which can generate problems. The maintainer then
	tries to uncover them thanks to advanced users who can manage
	important issues. After this first stage, the package is moved into
	<emphasis role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>, where it reaches
	a much larger audience and where it will be tested in much more
	detail.</para>

	<para><emphasis role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis> is
	generally used by users who do not mind breaking their system and
	then repairing it. This distribution gives the possibility to
	import a package which a user wants to try or use as the need
	arises. That is exactly how Debian approaches it, since adding it
	in APT's <filename>sources.list</filename> file does not lead to
	the systematic use of its packages. The line to be added is:</para>
        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>deb http://ftp.debian.org/debian experimental main contrib non-free
</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Non-Official Resources: <literal>apt-get.org</literal> and <literal>mentors.debian.net</literal></title>
      <indexterm><primary><literal>apt-get.org</literal></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><literal>mentors.debian.net</literal></primary></indexterm>

      <para>There are numerous non-official sources of Debian packages set
      up by advanced users who have recompiled some software, by
      programmers who make their creation available to all, and even by
      Debian developers who offer pre-versions of their package online. A
      web site was set up to find these alternative sources more easily. It
      contains an impressive amount of Debian package sources which can
      immediately be integrated into <filename>sources.list</filename>
      files. However, be careful not to add random packages. Each source is
      designed for a particular version of Debian (the one used to compile
      the packages in question); each user should maintain a certain
      coherence in what they choose to install. <ulink type="block"
      url="http://www.apt-get.org/"/></para>

      <para>The <literal>mentors.debian.net</literal> site is also
      interesting, since it gathers source packages created by candidates to the
      status of official Debian developer or by volunteers who wish to
      create Debian packages without going through that process of
      integration. These packages are made available without any guarantee
      regarding their quality; make sure that you check their origin and
      integrity and then test them before you consider using them in
      production.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>COMMUNITY</emphasis> The <literal>debian.net</literal> sites</title>
        <indexterm><primary><emphasis>debian.net</emphasis></primary></indexterm>

	<para>The <emphasis>debian.net</emphasis> domain is not an official
	resource of the Debian project. Each Debian developer may use that
	domain name for their own use. These websites can contain
	unofficial services (sometimes personal sites) hosted on a machine
	which does not belong to the project and set up by Debian
	developers, or even prototypes about to be moved on to
	<emphasis>debian.org</emphasis>. Two reasons can explain why some
	of these prototypes remain on <emphasis>debian.net</emphasis>:
	either no one has made the necessary effort to transform it into an
	official service (hosted on the <emphasis>debian.org</emphasis>
	domain, and with a certain guarantee of maintenance), or the
	service is too controversial to be officialized.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <para>Installing a package means giving root rights to its creator,
      because they decide on the contents of the initialization scripts
      which are run under that identity. Official Debian packages are
      created by volunteers who have been co-opted and reviewed and who can
      seal their packages so that their origin and integrity can be
      checked.</para>

      <para>In general, be wary of a package whose origin you don't know
      and which isn't hosted on one of the official Debian servers:
      evaluate the degree to which you can trust the creator, and check the
      integrity of the package. <ulink type="block"
      url="http://mentors.debian.net/"/></para>

      <sidebar id="sidebar.snapshot.debian.org">
        <title><emphasis>GOING FURTHER</emphasis> Old package versions: <literal>snapshot.debian.org</literal></title>
        <indexterm><primary><literal>snapshot.debian.org</literal></primary></indexterm>

	<para>A new service (introduced in April 2010) can be used to “go
	backwards in time” and to find an old version of a package. It
	can be used for example to identify which version of a package
	introduced a regression, and more concretely, to come back to the
	former version while waiting for the regression fix.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Caching Proxy for Debian Packages</title>
      <indexterm><primary>proxy cache</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>cache, proxy</primary></indexterm>

      <para>When an entire network of machines is configured to use the same
      remote server to download the same updated packages, any administrator
      knows that it would be beneficial to have an intermediate proxy acting
      as a network-local cache (see sidebar <xref linkend="sidebar.cache" />).</para>

      <para>You can configure APT to use a "standard" proxy (see <xref
      linkend="sect.apt-config" /> for the APT side, and <xref
      linkend="sect.http-ftp-proxy" /> for the proxy side), but the Debian
      ecosystem offers better options to solve this problem. The dedicated
      software presented in this section are smarter than a plain proxy
      cache because they can rely on the specific structure of APT
      repositories (for instance they know when individual files are
      obsolete or not, and thus adjust the time during which they are
      kept).</para>

      <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">apt-cacher</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">apt-cacher-ng</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
      <para><emphasis role="pkg">apt-cacher</emphasis> and
      <emphasis role="pkg">apt-cacher-ng</emphasis> work like usual
      proxy cache servers. APT's <filename>sources.list</filename> is left
      unchanged, but APT is configured to use them as proxy for outgoing
      requests.</para>
      
      <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">approx</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
      <para><emphasis role="pkg">approx</emphasis>, on the other hand, acts
      like an HTTP server that “mirrors” any number of remote repositories
      in its top-level URLs. The mapping between those top-level directories and
      the remote URLs of the repositories is stored in
      <filename>/etc/approx/approx.conf</filename>:</para>

      <programlisting>
# &lt;name&gt; &lt;repository-base-url&gt;
debian   http://ftp.debian.org/debian
security http://security.debian.org
</programlisting>

      <para><emphasis role="pkg">approx</emphasis> runs by default on
      port 9999 via inetd (see <xref linkend="sect.inetd" />) and requires
      the users to adjust their <filename>sources.list</filename> file to point
      to the approx server:</para>

      <programlisting># Sample sources.list pointing to a local approx server
deb http://apt.falcot.com:9999/security wheezy/updates main contrib non-free
deb http://apt.falcot.com:9999/debian wheezy main contrib non-free
      </programlisting>
    </section>

  </section>
  <section id="sect.apt-get">
    <title><command>aptitude</command> and <command>apt-get</command> Commands</title>
    <indexterm><primary><command>apt-get</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude</command></primary></indexterm>

    <para>APT is a vast project, whose original plans included a graphical
    interface. It is based on a library which contains the core
    application, and <command>apt-get</command> is the first front end —
    command-line based — which was developed within the project.</para>

    <para>Numerous other graphical interfaces then appeared as external
    projects: <command>synaptic</command>, <command>aptitude</command>
    (which includes both a text mode interface and a graphical one — even
    if not complete yet), <command>wajig</command>, etc. The most
    recommended interface, <command>apt-get</command>, is the one used
    during the installation of Debian, and the one that we will use
    in the examples given in this section. Note however that
    <command>aptitude</command>'s command-line syntax is very similar.
    When there are major differences between <command>apt-get</command> and
    <command>aptitude</command>, these differences will be detailed.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Initialization</title>

      <!-- MAY CHANGE: size of Packages/Sources/Translation files
	   Packages: 7Mb Translation: 3Mb -->
      <para>For any work with APT, the list of available packages needs to
      be updated; this can be done simply through <command>apt-get
      update</command>. Depending on the speed of your connection, the
      operation can take a while since it involves downloading a certain
      number of <filename>Packages</filename>/<filename>Sources</filename>/<filename>Translation-<replaceable>language-code</replaceable></filename> files, which have gradually become
      bigger and bigger as Debian has developed (at least 10 MB of data for the
      <literal>main</literal> section). Of course, installing from a CD-ROM
      set does not require any downloading — in this case, the operation
      is very fast.</para>
      <indexterm><primary><command>apt-get update</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude update</command></primary></indexterm>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Installing and Removing</title>
      <indexterm><primary>package</primary><secondary>installation</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>package</primary><secondary>removal</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>installation</primary><secondary>package installation</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>removal of a package</primary></indexterm>

      <para>With APT, packages can be added or removed from the system,
      respectively with <command>apt-get install
      <replaceable>package</replaceable></command> and <command>apt-get
      remove <replaceable>package</replaceable></command>. In both cases,
      APT will automatically install the necessary dependencies or delete
      the packages which depend on the package that is being removed. The
      <command>apt-get purge <replaceable>package</replaceable></command>
      command involves a complete uninstallation — the configuration files
      are also deleted.</para>
      <indexterm><primary><command>apt-get install</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>apt-get remove</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>apt-get purge</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude install</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude remove</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude purge</command></primary></indexterm>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> Installing the same selection of packages several times</title>

	<para>It can be useful to systematically install the same list of
	packages on several computers. This can be done quite
	easily.</para>

	<para>First, retrieve the list of packages installed on the
	computer which will serve as the “model” to copy.</para>

        <screen><computeroutput>$ </computeroutput><userinput>dpkg --get-selections &gt;pkg-list</userinput>
</screen>

	<para>The <filename>pkg-list</filename> file then contains the list
	of installed packages. Next, transfer the
	<filename>pkg-list</filename> file on the computers you want to
	update and use the following commands:</para>

        <screen>## Update dpkg's database of known packages
# <userinput>avail=`mktemp`</userinput>
# <userinput>apt-cache dumpavail &gt; "$avail"</userinput>
# <userinput>dpkg --merge-avail "$avail"</userinput>
# <userinput>rm -f "$avail"</userinput>
## Update dpkg's selections
# <userinput>dpkg --set-selections &lt; pkg-list</userinput>
## Ask apt-get to install the selected packages
# <userinput>apt-get dselect-upgrade</userinput>
</screen>

	<para>The first commands records the list of available packages
	in the dpkg database, then <command>dpkg --set-selections</command>
	restores the selection of packages that you wish to install, and the
	<command>apt-get</command> invocation executes
	the required operations! <command>aptitude</command> does not have
	this command.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <sidebar role="important">
        <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> Removing and installing at the same time</title>

	<para>It is possible to ask <command>apt-get</command> (or
	<command>aptitude</command>) to install certain packages and remove
	others on the same command line by adding a suffix. With an
	<command>apt-get install</command> command, add
	“<literal>-</literal>” to the names of the packages you wish to
	remove. With an <command>apt-get remove</command> command, add
	“<literal>+</literal>” to the names of the packages you wish to
	install.</para>

	<para>The next example shows two different ways to install
	<replaceable>package1</replaceable> and to remove
	<replaceable>package2</replaceable>.</para>

        <screen># <userinput>apt-get install <replaceable>package1</replaceable> <replaceable>package2-</replaceable></userinput>
[...]
# <userinput>apt-get remove <replaceable>package1+</replaceable> <replaceable>package2</replaceable></userinput>
[...]
</screen>

	<para>This can also be used to exclude packages which would
	otherwise be installed, for example due to a
	<literal>Recommends</literal>. In general, the dependency solver
	will use that information as a hint to look for alternative
	solutions.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> <command>apt-get --reinstall</command> and <command>aptitude reinstall</command></title>
        <indexterm><primary>reinstallation</primary></indexterm>

	<para>The system can sometimes be damaged after the removal or
	modification of files in a package. The easiest way to retrieve
	these files is to reinstall the affected package. Unfortunately,
	the packaging system finds that the latter is already installed and
	politely refuses to reinstall it; to avoid this, use the
	<literal>--reinstall</literal> option of the
	<command>apt-get</command> command. The following command
	reinstalls <emphasis role="pkg">postfix</emphasis> even if it is
	already present:</para>

        <screen><computeroutput># </computeroutput><userinput>apt-get --reinstall install postfix</userinput>
</screen>

	<para>The <command>aptitude</command> command line is slightly
	different, but achieves the same result with <command>aptitude
	reinstall postfix</command>.</para>

	<para>The problem does not arise with <command>dpkg</command>, but
	the administrator rarely uses it directly.</para>

	<para>Be careful, using <command>apt-get --reinstall</command> to
	restore packages modified during an attack certainly cannot recover
	the system as it was. <xref
	linkend="sect.dealing-with-compromised-machine"/> details the
	necessary steps to take with a compromised system.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <para>If the file <filename>sources.list</filename> mentions several
      distributions, it is possible to give the version of the package to
      install. A specific version number can be requested with
      <command>apt-get install
      <replaceable>package</replaceable>=<replaceable>version</replaceable></command>,
      but indicating its distribution of origin (<emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>) — with <command>apt-get
      install
      <replaceable>package</replaceable>/<replaceable>distribution</replaceable></command>
      — is usually preferred. With this command, it is possible to go
      back to an older version of a package (if for instance you know that
      it works well), provided that it is still available in one of the
      sources referenced by the <filename>sources.list</filename> file.
      Otherwise the <literal>snapshot.debian.org</literal> archive can come
      to the rescue (see sidebar <xref
      linkend="sidebar.snapshot.debian.org"/>).</para>

      <example>
        <title>Installation of the <emphasis role="distribution">unstable</emphasis> version of <emphasis role="pkg">spamassassin</emphasis></title>

        <screen><computeroutput># </computeroutput><userinput>apt-get install spamassassin/unstable</userinput>
</screen>
      </example>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>GOING FURTHER</emphasis> The cache of <filename>.deb</filename> files</title>

	<para>APT keeps a copy of each downloaded <filename>.deb</filename>
	file in the directory
	<filename>/var/cache/apt/archives/</filename>. In case of frequent
	updates, this directory can quickly take a lot of disk space with
	several versions of each package; you should regularly sort through
	them. Two commands can be used: <command>apt-get clean</command>
	entirely empties the directory; <command>apt-get
	autoclean</command> only removes packages which cannot be
	downloaded (because they have disappeared from the Debian mirror)
	and are therefore clearly useless (the configuration parameter
	<literal>APT::Clean-Installed</literal> can prevent the removal of
	<filename>.deb</filename> files that are currently
	installed).</para>
      </sidebar>
    </section>

    <section id="sect.apt-upgrade">
      <title>System Upgrade</title>
      <indexterm><primary>upgrade</primary><secondary>system upgrade</secondary></indexterm>

      <indexterm><primary><command>apt-get upgrade</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude safe-upgrade</command></primary></indexterm>
      <para>Regular upgrades are recommended, because they include the
      latest security updates. To upgrade, use <command>apt-get
      upgrade</command> or <command>aptitude safe-upgrade</command> (of
      course after <command>apt-get update</command>). This command looks
      for installed packages which can be upgraded without removing any
      packages. In other words, the goal is to ensure the least intrusive
      upgrade possible. <command>apt-get</command> is slightly more
      demanding than <command>aptitude</command> because it will refuse to
      install packages which were not installed beforehand.</para>

      <sidebar id="sidebar.apt-pdiff">
        <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> Incremental upgrade</title>

	<!-- MAY CHANGE: size of Packages file -->
	<para>As we explained earlier, the aim of the <command>apt-get
	update</command> command is to download for each package source the
	corresponding <filename>Packages</filename> (or
	<filename>Sources</filename>) file. However, even after a
	<command>bzip2</command> compression, these files can remain rather
	large (the <filename>Packages.bz2</filename> for the
	<foreignphrase>main</foreignphrase> section of <emphasis
	role="distribution">Wheezy</emphasis> takes more than 5 MB). If
	you wish to upgrade regularly, these downloads can take up a lot of
	time.</para>

	<para>To speed up the process APT can download “diff” files containing
	the changes since the previous update, as opposed to the entire
	file. To achieve this, official Debian mirrors distribute different
	files which list the differences between one version of the
	<filename>Packages</filename> file and the following version. They
	are generated at each update of the archives and a history of one
	week is kept. Each of these “diff” files only takes a few dozen
	kilobytes for <emphasis role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>, so
	that the amount of data downloaded by a weekly <command>aptitude
	update</command> is often divided by 10. For distributions like
	<emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> and <emphasis
	role="distribution">Testing</emphasis>, which change less, the gain
	is even more noticeable.</para>

	<para>However, it can sometimes be of interest to force the
	download of the entire <filename>Packages</filename> file,
	especially when the last upgrade is very old and when the mechanism
	of incremental differences would not contribute much. This can also
	be interesting when network access is very fast but when the
	processor of the machine to upgrade is rather slow, since the time
	saved on the download is more than lost when the computer
	calculates the new versions of these files (starting with the older
	versions and applying the downloaded differences). To do that, you
	can use the configuration parameter
	<literal>Acquire::Pdiffs</literal> and set it to
	<literal>false</literal>.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <para><command>apt-get</command> will generally select the most
      recent version number (except for packages from <emphasis
      role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis> and
      <emphasis role="distribution">stable-backports</emphasis>, which are
      ignored by default whatever their version number). If you specified
      <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> in your
      <filename>sources.list</filename>, <command>apt-get
      upgrade</command> will switch most of your <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> system to <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>, which might not be what you
      intended.</para>

      <para>To tell <command>apt-get</command> to use a specific
      distribution when searching for upgraded packages, you need to use
      the <literal>-t</literal> or <literal>--target-release</literal>
      option, followed by the name of the
      distribution you want (for example: <command>apt-get -t stable
      upgrade</command>). To avoid specifying this option every time
      you use <command>apt-get</command>, you can add
      <literal>APT::Default-Release "stable";</literal> in the file
      <filename>/etc/apt/apt.conf.d/local</filename>.</para>

      <indexterm><primary><command>apt-get dist-upgrade</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude dist-upgrade</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude full-upgrade</command></primary></indexterm>

      <para>For more important upgrades, such as the change from one major
      Debian version to the next, you need to use <command>apt-get
      dist-upgrade</command> (“distribution upgrade”).
      With this instruction, <command>apt-get</command> will complete the
      upgrade even if it has to remove some obsolete packages or install
      new dependencies. This is also the command used by users who work
      daily with the Debian <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> release and follow its
      evolution day by day. It is so simple that it hardly needs
      explanation: APT's reputation is based on this great
      functionality.</para>

      <para><command>aptitude full-upgrade</command> is
      <command>aptitude</command>'s corresponding command although
      <command>dist-upgrade</command> is also recognized (but deprecated).
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="sect.apt-config">
      <title>Configuration Options</title>
      <indexterm><primary>APT</primary><secondary>configuration</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><filename>apt.conf.d/</filename></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><filename>/etc/apt/apt.conf.d/</filename></primary></indexterm>

      <para>Besides the configuration elements already mentioned, it is
      possible to configure certain aspects of APT by adding directives in
      a file of the <filename>/etc/apt/apt.conf.d/</filename> directory.
      Remember for instance that it is possible for APT to tell
      <command>dpkg</command> to ignore file conflict errors by specifying
      <literal>DPkg::Options { "--force-overwrite"; }</literal>.</para>

      <para>If the Web can only be accessed through a proxy, add a line
      like <literal>Acquire::http::proxy
      "http://<replaceable>yourproxy</replaceable>:3128"</literal>. For an
      FTP proxy, write <literal>Acquire::ftp::proxy
      "ftp://<replaceable>yourproxy</replaceable>"</literal>. To discover
      more configuration options, read the
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>apt.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>
      manual page with the <command>man apt.conf</command> command (for
      details on manual pages, see <xref linkend="sect.manual-pages" />).</para>

      <sidebar id="sidebar.directory.d">
        <title><emphasis>BACK TO BASICS</emphasis> Directories ending in <filename>.d</filename></title>
        <indexterm><primary><filename>.d</filename></primary></indexterm>

	<para>Directories with a <filename>.d</filename> suffix are used
	more and more often. Each directory represents a configuration file
	which is split over multiple files. In this sense, all of the files
	in <filename>/etc/apt/apt.conf.d/</filename> are instructions for
	the configuration of APT. APT includes them in alphabetical order,
	so that the last ones can modify a configuration element defined in
	one of the first ones.</para>

	<para>This structure brings some flexibility to the machine
	administrator and to the package maintainers. Indeed, the
	administrator can easily modify the configuration of the software
	by adding a ready-made file in the directory in question without
	having to change an existing file. Package maintainers use the same
	approach when they need to adapt the configuration of another
	software to ensure that it perfectly co-exists with theirs.
	The Debian policy explicitly forbids modifying
	configuration files of other packages — only users are allowed to
	do this. Remember that during a package upgrade, the user gets to
	choose the version of the configuration file that should be kept
	when a modification has been detected. Any external modification of
	the file would trigger that request, which would disturb the
	administrator, who is sure not to have changed anything.</para>

	<para>Without a <filename>.d</filename> directory, it is impossible
	for an external package to change the settings of a program without
	modifying its configuration file. Instead it must invite the user
	to do it himself and lists the operations to be done in the file
	<filename>/usr/share/doc/<replaceable>package</replaceable>/README.Debian</filename>.</para>

	<para>Depending on the application, the <filename>.d</filename>
	directory is used directly or managed by an external script which
	will concatenate all the files to create the configuration file
	itself. It is important to execute the script after any change in
	that directory so that the most recent modifications are taken into
	account. In the same way, it is important not to work directly in
	the configuration file created automatically, since everything
	would be lost at the next execution of the script. The chosen
	method (<filename>.d</filename> directory used directly or a file
	generated from that directory) is usually dictated by implementation
	constraints, but in both cases the gains in terms of configuration
	flexibility more than make up for the small complications that they
	entail. The Exim 4 mail server is an example of the generated file
	method: it can be configured through several files
	(<filename>/etc/exim4/conf.d/*</filename>) which are concatenated
	into <filename>/var/lib/exim4/config.autogenerated</filename> by
	the <command>update-exim4.conf</command> command.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
    <section id="sect.apt.priorities">
      <title>Managing Package Priorities</title>

      <para>One of the most important aspects in the configuration of APT
      is the management of the priorities associated with each package
      source. For instance, you might want to extend one distribution with
      one or two newer packages from <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis>. It is possible to assign
      a priority to each available package (the same package can have
      several priorities depending on its version or the distribution
      providing it). These priorities will influence APT's behavior: for
      each package, it will always select the version with the highest
      priority (except if this version is older than the installed one and
      if its priority is less than 1000).</para>
      <indexterm><primary>APT</primary><secondary><foreignphrase>pinning</foreignphrase></secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>pinning, APT pinning</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>package</primary><secondary>priority</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>priority</primary><secondary>package priority</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>APT</primary><secondary>preferences</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><filename>preferences</filename></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><filename>/etc/apt/preferences</filename></primary></indexterm>

      <para>APT defines several default priorities. Each installed package
      version has a priority of 100. A non-installed version has a
      priority of 500 by default, but it can jump to 990 if it is part of
      the target release (defined with the <literal>-t</literal>
      command-line option or the <literal>APT::Default-Release</literal>
      configuration directive).</para>

      <para>You can modify the priorities by adding entries in the
      <filename>/etc/apt/preferences</filename> file with the names of the
      affected packages, their version, their origin and their new
      priority.</para>

      <para>APT will never install an older version of a package (that is,
      a package whose version number is lower than the one of the currently
      installed package) except if its priority is higher than 1000. APT
      will always install the highest priority package which follows this
      constraint. If two packages have the same priority, APT installs the
      newest one (whose version number is the highest). If two packages of
      same version have the same priority but differ in their content, APT
      installs the version that is not installed (this rule has been
      created to cover the case of a package update without the increment
      of the revision number, which is usually required).</para>

      <para>In more concrete terms, a package whose priority is less
      than 0 will never be installed. A package with a priority ranging
      between 0 and 100 will only be installed if no other version of the
      package is already installed. With a priority between 100 and 500,
      the package will only be installed if there is no other newer version
      installed or available in another distribution. A package of priority
      between 501 and 990 will only be installed if there is no newer
      version installed or available in the target distribution. With a
      priority between 990 and 1000, the package will be installed except
      if the installed version is newer. A priority greater than 1000 will
      always lead to the installation of the package even if it forces APT
      to downgrade to an older version.</para>

      <para>When APT checks <filename>/etc/apt/preferences</filename>, it
      first takes into account the most specific entries (often those
      specifying the concerned package), then the more generic ones
      (including for example all the packages of a distribution). If
      several generic entries exist, the first match is used. The available
      selection criteria include the package's name and the source
      providing it. Every package source is identified by the information
      contained in a <filename>Release</filename> file that APT downloads
      together with the <filename>Packages</filename> files. It
      specifies the origin (usually “Debian” for the packages of
      official mirrors, but it can also be a person's or an organization's
      name for third-parties repositories). It also gives the name of the
      distribution (usually <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis>, <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis> for the standard
      distributions provided by Debian) together with its version (for
      example 5.0 for Debian <emphasis
      role="distribution">Lenny</emphasis>). Let's have a look at its
      syntax through some realistic case studies of this mechanism.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>SPECIFIC CASE</emphasis> Priority of <emphasis role="distribution">experimental</emphasis></title>
        <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis></primary></indexterm>

	<para>If you listed <emphasis
	role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis> in your
	<filename>sources.list</filename> file, the corresponding packages
	will almost never be installed because their default APT priority
	is 1. This is of course a specific case, designed to keep users
	from installing <emphasis
	role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis> packages by mistake.
	The packages can only be installed by typing <command>aptitude
	install <replaceable>package</replaceable>/experimental</command>
	— users typing this command can only be aware of the risks that
	they take. It is still possible (though <emphasis>not</emphasis>
	recommended) to treat packages of <emphasis
	role="distribution">Experimental</emphasis> like those of other
	distributions by giving them a priority of 500. This is done with
	a specific entry in
	<filename>/etc/apt/preferences</filename>:</para>
        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>Package: *
Pin: release a=experimental
Pin-Priority: 500
</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </sidebar>

      <para>Let's suppose that you only want to use packages from the
      stable version of Debian. Those provided in other versions should not
      be installed except if explicitly requested. You could write the
      following entries in the <filename>/etc/apt/preferences</filename>
      file:</para>
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting>Package: *
Pin: release a=stable
Pin-Priority: 900

Package: *
Pin: release o=Debian
Pin-Priority: -10
</programlisting>
      </informalexample>

      <para><literal>a=stable</literal> defines the name of the selected
      distribution. <literal>o=Debian</literal> limits the scope to
      packages whose origin is “Debian”.</para>

      <para>Let's now assume that you have a server with several local
      programs depending on the version 5.14 of Perl and that you want to
      ensure that upgrades will not install another version of it. You
      could use this entry:</para>
      <informalexample>
        <programlisting>Package: perl
Pin: version 5.14*
Pin-Priority: 1001
</programlisting>
      </informalexample>

      <para>The reference documentation for this configuration file is
      available in the manual page
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>apt_preferences</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      which you can display with <command>man
      apt_preferences</command>.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> Comments in <filename>/etc/apt/preferences</filename></title>
        <indexterm><primary><literal>Explanation</literal></primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary><literal>Pin</literal></primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary><literal>Pin-Priority</literal></primary></indexterm>

	<para>There is no official syntax to put comments in the
	<filename>/etc/apt/preferences</filename> file, but some textual
	descriptions can be provided by putting one or more
	“<literal>Explanation</literal>” fields at the start of each
	entry:</para>
        <informalexample>
          <programlisting>Explanation: The package xserver-xorg-video-intel provided
Explanation: in experimental can be used safely
Package: xserver-xorg-video-intel
Pin: release a=experimental
Pin-Priority: 500
</programlisting>
        </informalexample>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
    <section id="sect.apt-mix-distros">
      <title>Working with Several Distributions</title>

      <para><command>apt-get</command> being such a marvelous tool, it is
      tempting to pick packages coming from other distributions. For
      example, after having installed a <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> system, you might want to try
      out a software package available in <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> without diverging too much
      from the system's initial state.</para>

      <para>Even if you will occasionally encounter problems while mixing
      packages from different distributions, <command>apt-get</command>
      manages such coexistence very well and limits risks very effectively.
      The best way to proceed is to list all distributions used in
      <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> (some people always put
      the three distributions, but remember that <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> is reserved for experienced
      users) and to define your reference distribution with the
      <literal>APT::Default-Release</literal> parameter (see <xref
      linkend="sect.apt-upgrade"/>).</para>

      <para>Let's suppose that <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> is your reference distribution
      but that <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> and
      <emphasis role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> are also listed in
      your <filename>sources.list</filename> file. In this case, you can
      use <command>apt-get install
      <replaceable>package</replaceable>/testing</command> to install a
      package from <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis>. If the
      installation fails due to some unsatisfiable dependencies, let it
      solve those dependencies within <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> by adding the <literal>-t
      testing</literal> parameter. The same obviously applies to <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>In this situation, upgrades (<command>upgrade</command>
      and <command>dist-upgrade</command>) are done within <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> except for packages already
      upgraded to another distribution: those will follow updates
      available in the other distributions. We'll explain this behavior
      with the help of the default priorities set by APT below. Do not
      hesitate to use <command>apt-cache policy</command> (see sidebar) to
      verify the given priorities.</para>

      <para>Everything centers around the fact that APT only considers
      packages of higher or equal version than the installed one (assuming
      that <filename>/etc/apt/preferences</filename> has not been used to
      force priorities higher than 1000 for some packages).</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> <command>apt-cache policy</command></title>

	<para>To gain a better understanding of the mechanism of priority,
	do not hesitate to execute <command>apt-cache policy</command> to
	display the default priority associated with each package source.
	You can also use <command>apt-cache policy
	<replaceable>package</replaceable></command> to display the
	priorities of all available versions of a given package.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <para>Let's assume that you have installed version 1 of a first
      package from <emphasis role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> and that
      version 2 and 3 are available respectively in <emphasis
      role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>. The installed version has a
      priority of 100 but the version available in <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> (the very same) has a priority
      of 990 (because it is part of the target release). Packages in
      <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> and <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> have a priority of 500 (the
      default priority of a non-installed version). The winner is thus
      version 1 with a priority of 990. The package “stays in <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis>”.</para>

      <para>Let's take the example of another package whose version 2 has
      been installed from <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis>.
      Version 1 is available in <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> and version 3 in <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>. Version 1 (of priority 990
      — thus lower than 1000) is discarded because it is lower than the
      installed version. This only leaves version 2 and 3, both of
      priority 500. Faced with this alternative, APT selects the newest
      version, the one from <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>.If you don't want a package
      installed from <emphasis role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> to
      migrate to <emphasis role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>, you
      have to assign a priority lower than 500 (490 for example) to
      packages coming from <emphasis
      role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis>. You can modify
      <filename>/etc/apt/preferences</filename> to this effect:</para>

      <programlisting>Package: *
Pin: release a=unstable
Pin-Priority: 490
</programlisting>
    </section>
    <section id="sect.automatic-tracking">
      <title>Tracking Automatically Installed Packages</title>

      <para>One of the essential functionalities of
      <command>apt-get</command> (which was initially specific to
      <command>aptitude</command>) is the tracking of packages installed
      only through dependencies. These packages are called “automatic”,
      and often include libraries for instance.</para>
      
      <para>With this information, when packages are removed, the package
      managers can compute a list of automatic packages that are
      no longer needed (because there's no “manually installed” packages
      depending on them). <command>apt-get autoremove</command> will get
      rid of those packages. <command>aptitude</command> does not have
      this command because it removes them automatically as soon as they
      are identified. Both programs include a clear message listing
      the affected packages.</para>

      <indexterm><primary><command>apt-mark auto</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>apt-mark manual</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude markauto</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude unmarkauto</command></primary></indexterm>
      <para>It is a good habit to mark as automatic any package that you
      don't need directly so that they are automatically removed when they
      aren't necessary anymore. <command>apt-mark auto
      <replaceable>package</replaceable></command> will mark the given
      package as automatic whereas <command>apt-mark manual
      <replaceable>package</replaceable></command> does the
      opposite. <command>aptitude markauto</command> and
      <command>aptitude unmarkauto</command> work in the same way
      although they offer more features for marking many packages
      at once (see <xref linkend="sect.aptitude" />). The console-based
      interactive interface of <command>aptitude</command> also
      makes it easy to review the “automatic flag” on many packages.</para>

      <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude why</command></primary></indexterm>
      <para>People might want to know why an automatically installed
      package is present on the system. To get this information from the
      command line, you can use <command>aptitude why
      <replaceable>package</replaceable></command> (<command>apt-get</command>
      has no similar feature):</para>

      <screen>$ <userinput>aptitude why python-debian</userinput>
i   aptitude         Recommends apt-xapian-index         
i A apt-xapian-index Depends    python-debian (&gt;= 0.1.15)
      </screen>

      <sidebar>
	<title><emphasis>ALTERNATIVE</emphasis> <command>deborphan</command> and <command>debfoster</command></title>

	<indexterm><primary><command>deborphan</command></primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary><command>debfoster</command></primary></indexterm>
	<para>In days where <command>apt-get</command> and <command>aptitude</command>
	were not able to track automatic packages, there were two utilities
	producing lists of unnecessary packages:
	<command>deborphan</command> and
	<command>debfoster</command>.</para>

	<para><command>deborphan</command> is the most rudimentary of
	both. It simply scans the <literal>libs</literal> and
	<literal>oldlibs</literal> sections (in the absence of
	supplementary instructions) looking for the packages that are
	currently installed and that no other packages depends on. The
	resulting list can then serve as a basis to remove unneeded
	packages.</para>

	<para><command>debfoster</command> has a more elaborate approach,
	very similar to APT's one: it maintains a
	list of packages that have been explicitly installed, and
	remembers what packages are really required between each
	invocation. If new packages appear on the system and if
	<command>debfoster</command> doesn't know them as required
	packages, they will be shown on the screen together with a list
	of their dependencies. The program then offers a choice: remove
	the package (possibly together with those that depend on it),
	mark it as explicitly required, or ignore it temporarily.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="sect.apt-cache">
    <title>The <command>apt-cache</command> Command</title>
    <indexterm><primary><command>apt-cache</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>APT</primary><secondary>package search</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>APT</primary><secondary>header display</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>search of packages</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>package</primary><secondary>search</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>The <command>apt-cache</command> command can display much of the
    information stored in APT's internal database. This information is a
    sort of cache since it is gathered from the different sources listed in
    the <filename>sources.list</filename> file. This happens during the
    <command>apt-get update</command> operation.</para>

    <sidebar id="sidebar.cache">
      <title><emphasis>VOCABULARY</emphasis> Cache</title>

      <para>A cache is a temporary storage system used to speed up frequent
      data access when the usual access method is expensive
      (performance-wise). This concept can be applied in numerous
      situations and at different scales, from the core of microprocessors
      up to high-end storage systems.</para>

      <para>In the case of APT, the reference <filename>Packages</filename>
      files are those located on Debian mirrors. That said, it would be
      very ineffective to go through the network for every search that we
      might want to do in the database of available packages. That is why
      APT stores a copy of those files (in
      <filename>/var/lib/apt/lists/</filename>) and searches are done
      within those local files. Similarly,
      <filename>/var/cache/apt/archives/</filename> contains a cache of
      already downloaded packages to avoid downloading them again if you
      need to reinstall them after a removal.</para>
    </sidebar>

    <indexterm><primary><command>apt-cache show</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>apt-cache search</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude show</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude search</command></primary></indexterm>
    <para>The <command>apt-cache</command> command can do keyword-based
    package searches with <command>apt-cache search
    <replaceable>keyword</replaceable></command>. It can also display the
    headers of the package's available versions with <command>apt-cache
    show <replaceable>package</replaceable></command>. This command
    provides the package's description, its dependencies, the name of its
    maintainer, etc. Note that <command>aptitude search</command> and
    <command>aptitude show</command> work in the same way.
    </para>

    <sidebar>
      <title><emphasis>ALTERNATIVE</emphasis> <command>axi-cache</command></title>
      <indexterm><primary><command>axi-cache</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">apt-xapian-index</emphasis></primary></indexterm>

      <para><command>apt-cache search</command> is a very rudimentary tool,
      basically implementing <command>grep</command> on package's
      descriptions. It often returns too many results or none at all when
      you include too many keywords.</para>

      <para><command>axi-cache search <replaceable>term</replaceable></command>,
      on the other hand, provides better results, sorted by relevancy. It
      uses the <emphasis>Xapian</emphasis> search engine and is part of
      the <emphasis role="pkg">apt-xapian-index</emphasis> package whichs indexes
      all package information (and more, like the <filename>.desktop</filename>
      files from all Debian packages). It knows about tags
      (see sidebar <xref linkend="sidebar.debtags" />) and returns results in a matter
      of milliseconds.</para>

      <screen>$ <userinput>axi-cache search package use::searching</userinput>
105 results found.
Results 1-20:
100% packagesearch - GUI for searching packages and viewing package information
98% debtags - Enables support for package tags
94% debian-goodies - Small toolbox-style utilities 
93% dpkg-awk - Gawk script to parse /var/lib/dpkg/{status,available} and Packages
93% goplay - games (and more) package browser using DebTags
[...]
87% apt-xapian-index - maintenance and search tools for a Xapian index of Debian packages
[...]
More terms: search debian searching strigi debtags bsearch libbsearch
More tags: suite::debian works-with::software:package role::program interface::commandline implemented-in::c++ admin::package-management use::analysing
`axi-cache more' will give more results
      </screen>
    </sidebar>

    <indexterm><primary><command>apt-cache policy</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>apt-cache dumpavail</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>apt-cache pkgnames</command></primary></indexterm>
    <para>Some features are more rarely used. For instance,
    <command>apt-cache policy</command> displays the priorities of package
    sources as well as those of individual packages. Another example is
    <command>apt-cache dumpavail</command> which displays the headers of
    all available versions of all packages. <command>apt-cache
    pkgnames</command> displays the list of all the packages which appear
    at least once in the cache.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="sect.apt-frontends">
    <title>Frontends: <command>aptitude</command>, <command>synaptic</command></title>
    <indexterm><primary><command>aptitude</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>synaptic</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>APT</primary><secondary>interfaces</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>APT is a C++ program whose code mainly resides in the
    <command>libapt-pkg</command> shared library. Using a shared library
    facilitates the creation of user interfaces (front-ends), since the
    code contained in the library can easily be reused. Historically,
    <command>apt-get</command> was only designed as a test front-end for
    <command>libapt-pkg</command> but its success tends to obscure this
    fact.</para>
    <section id="sect.aptitude">
      <title><command>aptitude</command></title>

      <para><command>aptitude</command> is an interactive program that can
      be used in semi-graphical mode on the console. You can browse the
      list of installed and available packages, look up all the available
      information, and select packages to install or remove. The program is
      designed specifically to be used by administrators, so that its
      default behaviors are much more intelligent than
      <command>apt-get</command>'s, and its interface much easier to
      understand.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>The <command>aptitude</command> package manager</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/aptitude.png" scalefit="1" width="75%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>When it starts, <command>aptitude</command> shows a list of
      packages sorted by state (installed, non-installed, or installed but
      not available on the mirrors — other sections display tasks,
      virtual packages, and new packages that appeared recently on
      mirrors). To facilitate thematic browsing, other views are available.
      In all cases, <command>aptitude</command> displays a list combining
      categories and packages on the screen. Categories are organized
      through a tree structure, whose branches can respectively be unfolded
      or closed with the <keycombo><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo>,
      <keycombo><keycap>[</keycap></keycombo> and
      <keycombo><keycap>]</keycap></keycombo> keys.
      <keycombo><keycap>+</keycap></keycombo> should be used to mark a
      package for installation, <keycombo><keycap>-</keycap></keycombo> to
      mark it for removal and <keycombo><keycap>_</keycap></keycombo> to
      purge it (note than these keys can also be used for categories, in
      which case the corresponding actions will be applied to all the
      packages of the category). <keycombo><keycap>u</keycap></keycombo>
      updates the lists of available packages and <keycombo
      action="simul"><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>u</keycap></keycombo>
      prepares a global system upgrade.
      <keycombo><keycap>g</keycap></keycombo> switches to a summary view of
      the requested changes (and typing
      <keycombo><keycap>g</keycap></keycombo> again will apply the
      changes), and <keycombo><keycap>q</keycap></keycombo> quits the
      current view. If you are in the initial view, this will effectively
      close <command>aptitude</command>.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>DOCUMENTATION</emphasis> <command>aptitude</command></title>

	<para>This section does not cover the finer details of using
	<command>aptitude</command>, it rather focuses on giving you a
	survival kit to use it. <command>aptitude</command> is rather well
	documented and we advise you to use its complete manual available
	in the <emphasis role="pkg">aptitude-doc-en</emphasis> package.
	<ulink type="block"
	url="file:///usr/share/doc/aptitude/html/en/index.html"/></para>
      </sidebar>

      <para>To search for a package, you can type
      <keycombo><keycap>/</keycap></keycombo> followed by a search pattern.
      This pattern matches the name of the package, but can also be applied
      to the description (if preceded by <literal>~d</literal>), to the
      section (with <literal>~s</literal>) or to other characteristics
      detailed in the documentation. The same patterns can filter the list
      of displayed packages: type the
      <keycombo><keycap>l</keycap></keycombo> key (as in
      <foreignphrase>limit</foreignphrase>) and enter the pattern.</para>

      <para>Managing the “automatic flag” of Debian packages (see <xref
      linkend="sect.automatic-tracking" />) is a breeze with
      <command>aptitude</command>. It is possible to browse the list of
      installed packages and mark packages as automatic with <keycombo
      action="simul"><keycap>Shift</keycap> <keycap>m</keycap></keycombo>
      or to remove the mark with the
      <keycombo><keycap>m</keycap></keycombo> key. “Automatic packages”
      are tagged with an “A” in the list of packages. This feature also
      offers a simple way to visualize the packages in use on a machine,
      without all the libraries and dependencies that you don't really
      care about. The related pattern that can be used with
      <keycombo><keycap>l</keycap></keycombo> (to activate the filter
      mode) is <literal>~i!~M</literal>. It specifies that you only want
      to see installed packages (<literal>~i</literal>) not marked as
      automatic (<literal>!~M</literal>).</para> 
      
      <sidebar>
	<title><emphasis>TOOL</emphasis> Using <command>aptitude</command> on the command-line interface</title>

	<para>Most of <command>aptitude</command>'s features are
	accessible via the interactive interface as well as via
	command-lines. These command-lines will seem familiar to regular
	users of <command>apt-get</command> and
	<command>apt-cache</command>.</para>

	<para>The advanced features of <command>aptitude</command> are
	also available on the command-line. You can use the same package
	search patterns as in the interactive version. For example, if you
	want to cleanup the list of “manually installed” packages, and if
	you know that none of the locally installed programs require any
	particular libraries or Perl modules, you can mark the
	corresponding packages as automatic with a single command:</para>

	<screen><computeroutput># </computeroutput><userinput>aptitude markauto '~slibs|~sperl'</userinput>
</screen>

	<para>Here, you can clearly see the power of the search pattern
	system of <command>aptitude</command>, which enables the instant
	selection of all the packages in the <literal>libs</literal> and
	<literal>perl</literal> sections.</para>

	<para>Beware, if some packages are marked as automatic and if no
	other package depends on them, they will be removed immediately
	(after a confirmation request).</para>
      </sidebar>

      <section>
        <title>Managing Recommendations, Suggestions and Tasks</title>

	<para>Another interesting feature of <command>aptitude</command> is
	the fact that it respects recommendations between packages while
	still giving users the choice not to install them on a case by case
	basis. For example, the <emphasis
	role="pkg">gnome</emphasis> package recommends
	<emphasis role="pkg">gdebi</emphasis> (among others).
	When you select the former for installation, the latter will also
	be selected (and marked as automatic if not already installed on
	the system). Typing <keycombo><keycap>g</keycap></keycombo> will
	make it obvious: <emphasis
	role="pkg">gdebi</emphasis> appears on the summary
	screen of pending actions in the list of packages installed
	automatically to satisfy dependencies. However, you can decide not
	to install it by deselecting it before confirming the
	operations.</para>

	<para>Note that this recommendation tracking feature does not apply
	to upgrades. For instance, if a new version of <emphasis
	role="pkg">gnome</emphasis> recommends a
	package that it did not recommend formerly, the package won't be
	marked for installation. However, it will be listed on the upgrade
	screen so that the administrator can still select it for
	installation.</para>

	<para>Suggestions between packages are also taken into account, but
	in a manner adapted to their specific status. For example, since
	<emphasis role="pkg">gnome</emphasis> suggests
	<emphasis role="pkg">dia-gnome</emphasis>, the latter will be
	displayed on the summary screen of pending actions (in the section
	of packages suggested by other packages). This way, it is visible
	and the administrator can decide whether to take the suggestion
	into account or not. Since it is only a suggestion and not a
	dependency or a recommendation, the package will not be selected
	automatically — its selection requires a manual intervention from
	the user (thus, the package will not be marked as
	automatic).</para>

	<para>In the same spirit, remember that <command>aptitude</command>
	makes intelligent use of the concept of task. Since tasks are
	displayed as categories in the screens of packages lists, you can
	either select a full task for installation or removal, or browse
	the list of packages included in the task to select a smaller
	subset.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Better Solver Algorithms</title>

	<para>To conclude this section, let's note that
	<command>aptitude</command> has more elaborate algorithms compared
	to <command>apt-get</command> when it comes to resolving difficult
	situations. When a set of actions is requested and when these
	combined actions would lead to an incoherent system,
	<command>aptitude</command> evaluates several possible scenarios
	and presents them in order of decreasing relevance. However, these
	algorithms are not failproof. Fortunately there is always the
	possibility to manually select the actions to perform. When the
	currently selected actions lead to contradictions, the upper part
	of the screen indicates a number of “broken” packages (and you
	can directly navigate to those packages by pressing
	<keycombo><keycap>b</keycap></keycombo>). It is then possible to
	manually build a solution for the problems found. In particular,
	you can get access to the different available versions by simply
	selecting the package with
	<keycombo><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo>. If the selection of
	one of these versions solves the problem, you should not hesitate
	to use the function. When the number of broken packages gets down
	to zero, you can safely go to the summary screen of pending actions
	for a last check before you apply them.</para>

        <sidebar>
          <title><emphasis>NOTE</emphasis> <command>aptitude</command>'s log</title>

	  <para>Like <command>dpkg</command>, <command>aptitude</command>
	  keeps a trace of executed actions in its logfile
	  (<filename>/var/log/aptitude</filename>). However, since both
	  commands work at a very different level, you cannot find the same
	  information in their respective logfiles. While
	  <command>dpkg</command> logs all the operations executed on
	  individual packages step by step, <command>aptitude</command>
	  gives a broader view of high-level operations like a system-wide
	  upgrade.</para>

	  <para>Beware, this logfile only contains a summary of operations
	  performed by <command>aptitude</command>. If other front-ends (or
	  even <command>dpkg</command> itself) are occasionally used, then
	  <command>aptitude</command>'s log will only contain a partial
	  view of the operations, so you can't rely on it to build a
	  trustworthy history of the system.</para>
        </sidebar>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title><command>synaptic</command></title>

      <para><command>synaptic</command> is a graphical package manager for
      Debian which features a clean and efficient graphical interface based
      on GTK+/GNOME. Its many ready-to-use filters give fast access to
      newly available packages, installed packages, upgradable packages,
      obsolete packages and so on. If you browse through these lists, you
      can select the operations to be done on the packages (install,
      upgrade, remove, purge); these operations are not performed
      immediately, but put into a task list. A single click on a button
      then validates the operations, and they are performed in one
      go.</para>

      <figure>
        <title><command>synaptic</command> package manager</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/synaptic.png" scalefit="1" width="75%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.package-authentication">
    <title>Checking Package Authenticity</title>
    <indexterm><primary>package</primary><secondary>authenticity check</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>package</primary><secondary>seal</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>package</primary><secondary>signature</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>signature</primary><secondary>package signature</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>authentication</primary><secondary>package authentication</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>Security is very important for Falcot Corp administrators.
    Accordingly, they need to ensure that they only install packages which
    are guaranteed to come from Debian with no tampering on the way. A
    computer cracker could try to add malicious code to an otherwise
    legitimate package. Such a package, if installed, could do anything the
    cracker designed it to do, including for instance disclosing passwords
    or confidential information. To circumvent this risk, Debian provides a
    tamper-proof seal to guarantee — at install time — that a package
    really comes from its official maintainer and hasn't been modified by a
    third party.</para>

    <para>The seal works with a chain of cryptographical hashes and a
    signature. The signed file is the <filename>Release</filename> file,
    provided by the Debian mirrors. It contains a list of the
    <filename>Packages</filename> files (including their compressed forms,
    <filename>Packages.gz</filename> and <filename>Packages.bz2</filename>,
    and the incremental versions), along with their MD5, SHA1 and SHA256
    hashes, which ensures that the files haven't been tampered with. These
    <filename>Packages</filename> files contain a list of the Debian
    packages available on the mirror, along with their hashes, which
    ensures in turn that the contents of the packages themselves haven't
    been altered either.</para>

    <indexterm><primary><command>apt-key</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">debian-archive-keyring</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><filename>/etc/apt/trusted.gpg.d/</filename></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><filename>Release.gpg</filename></primary></indexterm>
    <para>The trusted keys are managed with the <command>apt-key</command>
    command found in the <emphasis role="pkg">apt</emphasis> package. This
    program maintains a keyring of GnuPG public keys, which are used to
    verify signatures in the <filename>Release.gpg</filename> files
    available on the mirrors. It can be used to add new keys manually (when
    non-official mirrors are needed). Generally however, only the official
    Debian keys are needed. These keys are automatically kept up-to-date by
    the <emphasis role="pkg">debian-archive-keyring</emphasis> package
    (which puts the corresponding keyrings in <filename>/etc/apt/trusted.gpg.d</filename>).
    However, the first installation of this particular package
    requires caution: even if the package is signed like any other, the
    signature cannot be verified externally. Cautious administrators should
    therefore check the fingerprints of imported keys before trusting them
    to install new packages:</para>

    <screen role="scale"># <userinput>apt-key fingerprint</userinput>
/etc/apt/trusted.gpg.d//debian-archive-squeeze-automatic.gpg
------------------------------------------------------------
pub   4096R/473041FA 2010-08-27 [expires: 2018-03-05]
      Key fingerprint = 9FED 2BCB DCD2 9CDF 7626  78CB AED4 B06F 4730 41FA
uid                  Debian Archive Automatic Signing Key (6.0/squeeze) &lt;ftpmaster@debian.org&gt;

/etc/apt/trusted.gpg.d//debian-archive-squeeze-stable.gpg
---------------------------------------------------------
pub   4096R/B98321F9 2010-08-07 [expires: 2017-08-05]
      Key fingerprint = 0E4E DE2C 7F3E 1FC0 D033  800E 6448 1591 B983 21F9
uid                  Squeeze Stable Release Key &lt;debian-release@lists.debian.org&gt;

/etc/apt/trusted.gpg.d//debian-archive-wheezy-automatic.gpg
-----------------------------------------------------------
pub   4096R/46925553 2012-04-27 [expires: 2020-04-25]
      Key fingerprint = A1BD 8E9D 78F7 FE5C 3E65  D8AF 8B48 AD62 4692 5553
uid                  Debian Archive Automatic Signing Key (7.0/wheezy) &lt;ftpmaster@debian.org&gt;

/etc/apt/trusted.gpg.d//debian-archive-wheezy-stable.gpg
--------------------------------------------------------
pub   4096R/65FFB764 2012-05-08 [expires: 2019-05-07]
      Key fingerprint = ED6D 6527 1AAC F0FF 15D1  2303 6FB2 A1C2 65FF B764
uid                  Wheezy Stable Release Key &lt;debian-release@lists.debian.org&gt;
</screen>

    <sidebar>
      <title><emphasis>IN PRACTICE</emphasis> Adding trusted keys</title>
      <indexterm><primary>trusted key</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>key</primary><secondary>APT's authentication keys</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>When a third-party package source is added to the
      <filename>sources.list</filename> file, APT needs to be told to trust
      the corresponding GPG authentication key (otherwise it will keep complaining
      that it can't ensure the authenticity of the packages coming from
      that repository). The first step is of course to get the public key.
      More often than not, the key will be provided as a small text file,
      which we'll call <filename>key.asc</filename> in the following
      examples.</para>

      <para>To add the key to the trusted keyring, the administrator can
      run <command>apt-key add &lt; key.asc</command>. Another way is to
      use the <command>synaptic</command> graphical interface: its
      “Authentication” tab in the
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu>
      <guisubmenu>Repositories</guisubmenu></menuchoice> menu gives the
      possibility of importing a key from the <filename>key.asc</filename>
      file.</para>

      <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">gui-apt-key</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
      <para>For people who would want a dedicated application and more
      details on the trusted keys, it is possible to use
      <command>gui-apt-key</command> (in the package of the same name), a
      small graphical user interface which manages the trusted keyring.
      </para>
    </sidebar>

    <para>Once the appropriate keys are in the keyring, APT will check the
    signatures before any risky operation, so that front-ends will display
    a warning if asked to install a package whose authenticity can't be
    ascertained.</para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.dist-upgrade">
    <title>Upgrading from One Stable Distribution to the Next</title>

    <para>One of the best-known features of Debian is its ability to
    upgrade an installed system from one stable release to the next:
    <foreignphrase>dist-upgrade</foreignphrase> — a well-known phrase —
    has largely contributed to the project's reputation. With a few
    precautions, upgrading a computer can take as little as a few minutes,
    or a few dozen minutes, depending on the download speed from the package
    repositories.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Recommended Procedure</title>

      <para>Since Debian has quite some time to evolve in-between stable
      releases, you should read the release notes before upgrading.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>BACK TO BASICS</emphasis> Release notes</title>

	<para>The release notes for an operating system (and, more
	generally, for any software) are a document giving an overview of
	the software, with some details concerning the particularities of
	one version. These documents are generally short compared to the
	complete documentation, and they usually list the features which
	have been introduced since the previous version. They also give
	details on upgrading procedures, warnings for users of previous
	versions, and sometimes errata.</para>

	<!-- MAY CHANGE: oldstable codename in URL -->
	<para>Release notes are available online: the release notes for the
	current stable release have a dedicated URL, while older release
	notes can be found with their codenames:
	<ulink type="block" url="http://www.debian.org/releases/stable/releasenotes"/>
	<ulink type="block" url="http://www.debian.org/releases/squeeze/releasenotes"/></para>
      </sidebar>

      <!-- MAY CHANGE: codenames -->
      <para>In this section, we will focus on upgrading a <emphasis
      role="distribution">Squeeze</emphasis> system to <emphasis
      role="distribution">Wheezy</emphasis>. This is a major operation on
      a system; as such, it is never 100% risk-free, and should not be
      attempted before all important data has been backed up.</para>

      <para>Another good habit which makes the upgrade easier (and
      shorter) is to tidy your installed packages and keep only the ones
      that are really needed. Helpful tools to do that include
      <command>aptitude</command>, <command>deborphan</command> and
      <command>debfoster</command> (see <xref
      linkend="sect.automatic-tracking"/>). For example, you can use the
      following command, and then use <command>aptitude</command>'s interactive
      mode to double check and fine-tune the scheduled removals:</para>

      <screen># <userinput>deborphan | xargs aptitude --schedule-only remove</userinput>
</screen>

      <para>Now for the upgrading itself. First, you need to change the
      <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> file to tell APT to get
      its packages from <emphasis role="distribution">Wheezy</emphasis>
      instead of <emphasis role="distribution">Squeeze</emphasis>. If the
      file only contains references to <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> rather than explicit codenames,
      the change isn't even required, since <emphasis
      role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> always refers to the latest
      released version of Debian. In both cases, the database of available
      packages must be refreshed (with the <command>apt-get
      update</command> command or the refresh button in
      <command>synaptic</command>).</para>

      <para>Once these new package sources are registered, you should
      first do a minimal upgrade with <command>apt-get upgrade</command>.
      By doing the upgrade in two steps, we ease the job of the
      package management tools and often ensure that we have the latest
      versions of those, which might have accumulated bugfixes and
      improvements required to complete the full distribution upgrade.
      </para>

      <para>Once this first upgrade is done, it is time to handle the
      upgrade itself, either with <command>apt-get dist-upgrade</command>,
      <command>aptitude</command>, or
      <command>synaptic</command>. You should carefully check the suggested
      actions before applying them: you might want to add suggested
      packages or deselect packages which are only recommended and known
      not to be useful. In any case, the front-end should come up with a
      scenario ending in a coherent and up-to-date <emphasis
      role="distribution">Wheezy</emphasis> system. Then, all you need is
      to do is wait while the required packages are downloaded, answer the
      Debconf questions and possibly those about locally modified
      configuration files, and sit back while APT does its magic.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Handling Problems after an Upgrade</title>

      <para>In spite of the Debian maintainers' best efforts, a major
      system upgrade isn't always as smooth as you could wish. New software
      versions may be incompatible with previous ones (for instance, their
      default behavior or their data format may have changed). Also, some
      bugs may slip through the cracks despite the testing phase which
      always precedes a Debian release.</para>

      <para>To anticipate some of these problems, you can install the
      <emphasis role="pkg">apt-listchanges</emphasis> package, which
      displays information about possible problems at the beginning of a
      package upgrade. This information is compiled by the package
      maintainers and put in
      <filename>/usr/share/doc/<replaceable>package</replaceable>/NEWS.Debian</filename>
      files for the benefit of users. Reading these files (possibly through
      <emphasis role="pkg">apt-listchanges</emphasis>) should help you
      avoid bad surprises.</para>

      <para>You might sometimes find that the new version of a software
      doesn't work at all. This generally happens if the application isn't
      particularly popular and hasn't been tested enough; a last-minute
      update can also introduce regressions which are only found after the
      stable release. In both cases, the first thing to do is to have a
      look at the bug tracking system at
      <literal>http://bugs.debian.org/<replaceable>package</replaceable></literal>,
      and check whether the problem has already been reported. If it
      hasn't, you should report it yourself with
      <command>reportbug</command>. If it is already known, the bug report
      and the associated messages are usually an excellent source of
      information related to the bug:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
	  <para>sometimes a patch already exists, and it is available on
	  the bug report; you can then recompile a fixed version of the
	  broken package locally (see <xref
	  linkend="sect.rebuilding-package"/>);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para>in other cases, users may have found a workaround for the
	  problem and shared their insights about it in their replies to
	  the report;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para>in yet other cases, a fixed package may have already been
	  prepared and made public by the maintainer.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Depending on the severity of the bug, a new version of the
      package may be prepared specifically for a new revision of the stable
      release. When this happens, the fixed package is made available in
      the <literal>proposed-updates</literal> section of the Debian mirrors
      (see <xref linkend="sect.proposed-updates"/>). The corresponding
      entry can then be temporarily added to the
      <filename>sources.list</filename> file, and updated packages can be
      installed with <command>apt-get</command> or
      <command>aptitude</command>.</para>

      <para>Sometimes the fixed package isn't available in this section yet
      because it is pending a validation by the Stable Release Managers.
      You can verify if that's the case on their web page. Packages listed
      there aren't available yet, but at least you know that the
      publication process is ongoing. <ulink type="block"
      url="http://release.debian.org/proposed-updates/stable.html"/></para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.regular-upgrades">
    <title>Keeping a System Up to Date</title>

    <para>The Debian distribution is dynamic and changes continually. Most
    of the changes are in the <emphasis
    role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> and <emphasis
    role="distribution">Unstable</emphasis> versions, but even <emphasis
    role="distribution">Stable</emphasis> is updated from time to time,
    mostly for security-related fixes. Whatever version of Debian a system
    runs, it is generally a good idea to keep it up to date, so that you
    can get the benefit of recent evolutions and bug fixes.</para>

    <para>While it is of course possible to periodically run a tool to
    check for available updates and run the upgrades, such a repetitive
    task is tedious, especially when it needs to be performed on several
    machines. Fortunately, like many repetitive tasks, it can be partly
    automated, and a set of tools have already been developed to that
    effect.</para>

    <para>The first of these tools is <command>apticron</command>, in the
    package of the same name. Its main effect is to run a script daily (via
    <command>cron</command>). The script updates the list of available
    packages, and, if some installed packages are not in the latest
    available version, it sends an email with a list of these packages
    along with the changes that have been made in the new versions.
    Obviously, this package mostly targets users of Debian <emphasis
    role="distribution">Stable</emphasis>, since the daily emails would be
    very long for the faster paced versions of Debian. When updates are
    available, <command>apticron</command> automatically downloads them. It
    does not install them — the administrator will still do it — but
    having the packages already downloaded and available locally (in APT's
    cache) makes the job faster.</para>

    <para>Administrators in charge of several computers will no doubt
    appreciate being informed of pending upgrades, but the upgrades
    themselves are still as tedious as they used to be, which is where the
    <filename>/etc/cron.daily/apt</filename> script (in the <emphasis
    role="pkg">apt</emphasis> package) comes in handy. This script is also
    run daily (and non-interactively) by <command>cron</command>. To
    control its behavior, use APT configuration variables (which are
    therefore stored in a file under
    <filename>/etc/apt/apt.conf.d/</filename>). The main three variables
    are:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <literal>APT::Periodic::Update-Package-Lists</literal>
        </term>
        <listitem>
	  <para>This option allows you to specify the frequency (in days)
	  at which the package lists are refreshed.
	  <command>apticron</command> users can do without this variable,
	  since <command>apticron</command> already does this task.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <literal>APT::Periodic::Download-Upgradeable-Packages</literal>
        </term>
        <listitem>
	  <para>Again, this option indicates a frequency (in days), this
	  time for the downloading of the actual packages. Again,
	  <command>apticron</command> users won't need it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <literal>APT::Periodic::AutocleanInterval</literal>
        </term>
        <listitem>
	  <para>This last option covers a feature that
	  <command>apticron</command> doesn't have. It controls how often
	  obsolete packages (those not referenced by any distribution
	  anymore) are removed from the APT cache. This keeps the APT cache
	  at a reasonable size and means that you don't need to worry about
	  that task.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <literal>APT::Periodic::Unattended-Upgrade</literal>
        </term>
        <listitem>
	  <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">unattended-upgrades</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
	  <para>When this option is enabled, the daily script will
	  execute <command>unattended-upgrade</command> (from the
	  <emphasis role="pkg">unattended-upgrades</emphasis> package)
	  which — as its name suggest — can automatize the upgrade
	  process for some packages (by default it only takes care of
	  security updates, but this can be customized in
	  <filename>/etc/apt/apt.conf.d/50unattended-upgrades</filename>).
	  Note that this option can be set with the help of debconf
	  by running <command>dpkg-reconfigure -plow unattended-upgrades</command>.
	  </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <para>Other options can allow you to control the cache cleaning
    behavior with more precision. They are not listed here, but they are
    described in the <filename>/etc/cron.daily/apt</filename>
    script.</para>

    <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">gnome-packagekit</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
    <para>These tools work very well for servers, but desktop users
    generally prefer a more interactive system. That is why the “Graphical
    desktop environment” task installs <emphasis
    role="pkg">gnome-packagekit</emphasis>. It provides an icon in the
    notification area of desktop environments when updates are available;
    clicking on this icon then runs <command>gpk-update-viewer</command>,
    a simplified interface to perform updates. You can browse through
    available updates, read the short description of the relevant packages
    and the corresponding <filename>changelog</filename> entries, and
    select whether to apply the update or not on a case-by-case
    basis.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Upgrading with <command>update-manager</command></title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/gnome-packagekit.png" scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="sect.automatic-upgrades">
    <title>Automatic Upgrades</title>
    <indexterm><primary>upgrade</primary><secondary>automatic system upgrade</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>automatic upgrade</primary></indexterm>

    <para>Since Falcot Corp has many computers but only limited manpower,
    its administrators try to make upgrades as automatic as possible. The
    programs in charge of these processes must therefore run with no human
    intervention.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Configuring <command>dpkg</command></title>

      <para>As we have already mentioned (see sidebar <xref
      linkend="sidebar.questions-conffiles"/>), <command>dpkg</command> can
      be instructed not to ask for confirmation when replacing a
      configuration file (with the <literal>--force-confdef
      --force-confold</literal> options). Interactions can, however, have
      three other sources: some come from APT itself, some are handled by
      <command>debconf</command>, and some happen on the command line due
      to package configuration scripts.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Configuring APT</title>

      <para>The case of APT is simple: the <literal>-y</literal> option (or
      <literal>--assume-yes</literal>) tells APT to consider the answer to
      all its questions to be “yes”.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Configuring <command>debconf</command></title>

      <para>The case of <command>debconf</command> deserves more details.
      This program was, from its inception, designed to control the
      relevance and volume of questions displayed to the user, as well as
      the way they are shown. That is why its configuration requests a
      minimal priority for questions; only questions above the minimal
      priority are displayed. <command>debconf</command> assumes the
      default answer (defined by the package maintainer) for questions
      which it decided to skip.</para>

      <para>The other relevant configuration element is the interface used
      by the front-end. If you choose <literal>noninteractive</literal> out
      of the choices, all user interaction is disabled. If a package tries
      to display an informative note, it will be sent to the administrator
      by email.</para>

      <para>To reconfigure <command>debconf</command>, use the
      <command>dpkg-reconfigure</command> tool from the <emphasis
      role="pkg">debconf</emphasis> package; the relevant command is
      <command>dpkg-reconfigure debconf</command>. Note that the configured
      values can be temporarily overridden with environment variables when
      needed (for instance, <varname>DEBIAN_FRONTEND</varname> controls the
      interface, as documented in the
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>debconf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7</manvolnum></citerefentry>
      manual page).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Handling Command Line Interactions</title>

      <para>The last source of interactions, and the hardest to get rid of,
      is the configuration scripts run by <command>dpkg</command>. There is
      unfortunately no standard solution, and no answer is overwhelmingly
      better than another.</para>

      <para>The common approach is to suppress the standard input by
      redirecting the empty content of <filename>/dev/null</filename> into
      it with <command><replaceable>command</replaceable>
      &lt;/dev/null</command>, or to feed it with an endless stream of
      newlines. None of these methods are 100 % reliable, but they
      generally lead to the default answers being used, since most scripts
      consider a lack of reply as an acceptance of the default
      value.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>The Miracle Combination</title>

      <para>By combining the previous elements, it is possible to design a
      small but rather reliable script which can handle automatic
      upgrades.</para>

      <example id="example.non-interactive-upgrade">
        <title>Non-interactive upgrade script</title>

        <programlisting>export DEBIAN_FRONTEND=noninteractive
yes '' | apt-get -y -o Dpkg::Options::="--force-confdef" -o Dpkg::Options::="--force-confold" dist-upgrade
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>IN PRACTICE</emphasis> The Falcot Corp case</title>

	<para>Falcot computers are a heterogeneous system, with machines
	having various functions. Administrators will therefore pick the
	most relevant solution for each computer.</para>

	<para>In practice, the servers running <emphasis
	role="distribution">Wheezy</emphasis> are configured with the
	“miracle combination” above, and are kept up to date
	automatically. Only the most critical servers (the firewalls, for
	instances) are set up with <command>apticron</command>, so that
	upgrades always happen under the supervision of an
	administrator.</para>

	<para>The office workstations in the administrative services also
	run <emphasis role="distribution">Wheezy</emphasis>, but they are
	equipped with <emphasis role="pkg">gnome-packagekit</emphasis>,
	so that users trigger the upgrades themselves. The
	rationale for this decision is that if upgrades happen without an
	explicit action, the behavior of the computer might change
	unexpectedly, which could cause confusion for the main
	users.</para>

	<para>In the lab, the few computers using <emphasis
	role="distribution">Testing</emphasis> — to take advantage of the
	latest software versions — are not upgraded automatically either.
	Administrators only configure APT to prepare the upgrades but not
	enact them; when they decide to upgrade (manually), the tedious
	parts of refreshing package lists and downloading packages will be
	avoided, and administrators can focus on the really useful
	part.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.searching-packages">
    <title>Searching for Packages</title>

    <para>With the large and ever-growing amount of software in Debian,
    there emerges a paradox: Debian usually has a tool for most tasks, but
    that tool can be very difficult to find amongst the myriad other
    packages. The lack of appropriate ways to search for (and to find) the
    right tool has long been a problem. Fortunately, this problem has
    almost entirely been solved.</para>

    <para>The most trivial search possible is looking up an exact package
    name. If <command>apt-cache show
    <replaceable>package</replaceable></command> returns a result, then the
    package exists. Unfortunately, this requires knowing or even guessing
    the package name, which isn't always possible.</para>

    <sidebar>
      <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> Package naming conventions</title>

      <para>Some categories of packages are named according to a
      conventional naming scheme; knowing the scheme can sometimes allow
      you to guess exact package names. For instance, for Perl modules, the
      convention says that a module called
      <literal>XML::Handler::Composer</literal> upstream should be packaged
      as <emphasis role="pkg">libxml-handler-composer-perl</emphasis>. The
      library enabling the use of the <command>gconf</command> system from
      Python is packaged as <emphasis role="pkg">python-gconf</emphasis>.
      It is unfortunately not possible to define a fully general naming
      scheme for all packages, even though package maintainers usually try
      to follow the choice of the upstream developers.</para>
    </sidebar>

    <para>A slightly more successful searching pattern is a plain-text
    search in package names, but it remains very limited. You can generally
    find results by searching package descriptions: since each package has
    a more or less detailed description in addition to its package name, a
    keyword search in these descriptions will often be useful.
    <command>apt-cache</command> and <command>axi-cache</command> are the
    tools of choice for this kind of
    search; for instance, <command>apt-cache search video</command> will
    return a list of all packages whose name or description contains the
    keyword “video”.</para>

    <para>For more complex searches, a more powerful tool such as
    <command>aptitude</command> is required. <command>aptitude</command>
    allows you to search according to a logical expression based on the
    package's meta-data fields. For instance, the following command
    searches for packages whose name contains <literal>kino</literal>,
    whose description contains <literal>video</literal> and whose
    maintainer's name contains <literal>paul</literal>:</para>

    <screen>$ <userinput>aptitude search kino~dvideo~mpaul</userinput>
p   kino  - Non-linear editor for Digital Video data
$ <userinput>aptitude show kino</userinput>
Package: kino                            
State: not installed
Version: 1.3.4-1.3
Priority: extra
Section: video
Maintainer: Paul Brossier &lt;piem@debian.org&gt;
Architecture: amd64
Uncompressed Size: 7936 k
Depends: libasound2 (&gt; 1.0.24.1), libatk1.0-0 (&gt;= 1.12.4),
         libavc1394-0 (&gt;= 0.5.3), libavcodec53 (&gt;= 4:0.8~beta1~) |
         libavcodec-extra-53 (&gt;= 4:0.8~beta1~), libavformat53
         […]
Recommends: ffmpeg, curl
Suggests: udev | hotplug, vorbis-tools, sox, mjpegtools, lame, ffmpeg2theora
Conflicts: kino-dvtitler, kino-timfx, kinoplus
Replaces: kino-dvtitler, kino-timfx, kinoplus
Provides: kino-dvtitler, kino-timfx, kinoplus
Description: Non-linear editor for Digital Video data
 Kino allows you to record, create, edit, and play movies recorded with
 DV camcorders. This program uses many keyboard commands for fast
 navigating and editing inside the movie.
 
 The kino-timfx, kino-dvtitler and kinoplus sets of plugins, formerly
 distributed as separate packages, are now provided with Kino.
Homepage: http://www.kinodv.org/

Tags: hardware::camera, implemented-in::c, implemented-in::c++,
      interface::x11, role::program, scope::application,
      suite::gnome, uitoolkit::gtk, use::editing, 
      works-with::video, x11::application
</screen>

    <para>The search only returns one package, <emphasis
    role="pkg">kino</emphasis>, which satisfies all three criteria.</para>

    <para>Even these multi-criteria searches are rather unwieldy, which
    explains why they are not used as much as they could. A new tagging
    system has therefore been developed, and it provides a new approach to
    searching. Packages are given tags that provide a thematical
    classification along several strands, known as a “facet-based
    classification”. In the case of <emphasis role="pkg">kino</emphasis>
    above, the package's tags indicate that Kino is a Gnome-based software
    that works on video data and whose main purpose is editing.</para>

    <para>Browsing this classification can help you to search for a package
    which corresponds to known needs; even if it returns a (moderate)
    number of hits, the rest of the search can be done manually. To do
    that, you can use the <literal>~G</literal> search pattern in
    <command>aptitude</command>, but it is probably easier to simply
    navigate the site where tags are managed:
    <ulink type="block" url="http://debtags.alioth.debian.org/cloud/"/>
    </para>

    <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">debtags</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>tag</primary></indexterm>
    <para>Selecting the <literal>works-with::video</literal> and
    <literal>use::editing</literal> tags yields a handful of packages,
    including the <emphasis role="pkg">kino</emphasis> and <emphasis
    role="pkg">pitivi</emphasis> video editors. This system of
    classification is bound to be used more and more as time goes on, and
    package managers will gradually provide efficient search interfaces
    based on it.</para>

    <para>To sum up, the best tool for the job depends on the complexity of
    the search that you wish to do:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para><command>apt-cache</command> only allows searching in package
	names and descriptions, which is very convenient when looking for a
	particular package that matches a few target keywords;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>when the search criteria also include relationships between
	packages or other meta-data such as the name of the maintainer,
	<command>synaptic</command> will be more useful;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>when a tag-based search is needed, a good tool is
	<command>packagesearch</command>, a graphical interface dedicated
	to searching available packages along several criteria (including
	the names of the files that they contain). For usage on the
	command-line, <command>axi-cache</command> will fit the bill.</para>
        <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">packagesearch</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary><command>axi-cache</command></primary></indexterm>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>finally, when the searches involve complex expressions with
	logic operations, the tool of choice will be
	<command>aptitude</command>'s search pattern syntax, which is quite
	powerful despite being somewhat obscure; it works in both the
	command-line and the interactive modes.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
