<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter id="network-infrastructure">
  <chapterinfo>
    <mediaobject condition="pdf">
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/chap-infrastructure.png" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Network</keyword>
      <keyword>Gateway</keyword>
      <keyword>TCP/IP</keyword>
      <keyword>IPv6</keyword>
      <keyword>DNS</keyword>
      <keyword>Bind</keyword>
      <keyword>DHCP</keyword>
      <keyword>QoS</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>
  <title id="infrastructure.title">Network Infrastructure</title>
  <highlights>
    <para>Linux sports the whole Unix heritage for networking, and Debian
    provides a full set of tools to create and manage them. This chapter
    reviews these tools.</para>
  </highlights>
  <section id="sect.gateway">
    <title>Gateway</title>

    <para>A gateway is a system linking several networks. This term often
    refers to a local network's “exit point” on the mandatory path to
    all external IP addresses. The gateway is connected to each of the
    networks it links together, and acts as a router to convey IP packets
    between its various interfaces.</para>
    <indexterm><primary>gateway</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>network</primary><secondary>gateway</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>router</primary></indexterm>

    <sidebar>
      <title><emphasis>BACK TO BASICS</emphasis> IP packet</title>
      <indexterm><primary>packet</primary><secondary>IP</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Most networks nowadays use the IP protocol (<emphasis>Internet
      Protocol</emphasis>). This protocol segments the transmitted data
      into limited-size packets. Each packet contains, in addition to its
      payload data, a number of details required for its proper
      routing.</para>
    </sidebar>

    <sidebar id="cadre.tcp-udp">
      <title><emphasis>BACK TO BASICS</emphasis> TCP/UDP</title>
      <indexterm><primary>port</primary><secondary>TCP</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>port</primary><secondary>UDP</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>TCP, port</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>UDP, port</primary></indexterm>

      <para>Many programs do not handle the individual packets themselves,
      even though the data they transmit does travel over IP; they often
      use TCP (<emphasis>Transmission Control Protocol</emphasis>). TCP is
      a layer over IP allowing the establishment of connections dedicated
      to data streams between two points. The programs then only see an
      entry point into which data can be fed with the guarantee that the
      same data exits without loss (and in the same sequence) at the exit
      point at the other end of the connection. Although many kinds of
      errors can happen in the lower layers, they are compensated by TCP:
      lost packets are retransmitted, and packets arriving out of order
      (for example, if they used different paths) are re-ordered
      appropriately.</para>

      <para>Another protocol relying on IP is UDP (<emphasis>User Datagram
      Protocol</emphasis>). In contrast to TCP, it is packet-oriented. Its
      goals are different: the purpose of UDP is only to transmit one
      packet from an application to another. The protocol does not try to
      compensate for possible packet loss on the way, nor does it ensure
      that packets are received in the same order as were sent. The main
      advantage to this protocol is that the latency is greatly improved,
      since the loss of a single packet does not delay the receiving of all
      following packets until the lost one is retransmitted.</para>

      <para>TCP and UDP both involve ports, which are “extension
      numbers” for establishing communication with a given application on
      a machine. This concept allows keeping several different
      communications in parallel with the same correspondent, since these
      communications can be distinguished by the port number.</para>

      <para>Some of these port numbers — standardized by the IANA
      (<emphasis>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</emphasis>) — are
      “well-known” for being associated with network services. For
      instance, TCP port 25 is generally used by the email server. <ulink
      type="block"
      url="http://www.iana.org/assignments/port-numbers"/></para>
    </sidebar>

    <para>When a local network uses a private address range (not routable
    on the Internet), the gateway needs to implement <emphasis>address
    masquerading</emphasis> so that the machines on the network can
    communicate with the outside world. The masquerading operation is a
    kind of proxy operating on the network level: each outgoing connection
    from an internal machine is replaced with a connection from the gateway
    itself (since the gateway does have an external, routable address), the
    data going through the masqueraded connection is sent to the new one,
    and the data coming back in reply is sent through to the masqueraded
    connection to the internal machine. The gateway uses a range of
    dedicated TCP ports for this purpose, usually with very high numbers
    (over 60000). Each connection coming from an internal machine then
    appears to the outside world as a connection coming from one of these
    reserved ports.</para>
    <indexterm><primary>masquerading</primary></indexterm>

    <sidebar>
      <title><emphasis>CULTURE</emphasis> Private address range</title>
      <indexterm><primary>IP address</primary><secondary>private</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>private, IP address</primary></indexterm>

      <para>RFC 1918 defines three ranges of IPv4 addresses not meant to
      be routed on the Internet but only used in local networks. The first
      one, <literal>10.0.0.0/8</literal> (see sidebar <xref
      linkend="sidebar.rappels-reseau"/>), is a class-A range (with
      2<superscript>24</superscript> IP addresses). The second one,
      <literal>172.16.0.0/12</literal>, gathers 16 class-B ranges
      (<literal>172.16.0.0/16</literal> to
      <literal>172.31.0.0/16</literal>), each containing
      2<superscript>16</superscript> IP addresses. Finally,
      <literal>192.168.0.0/16</literal> is a class-B range (grouping 256
      class-C ranges, <literal>192.168.0.0/24</literal> to
      <literal>192.168.255.0/24</literal>, with 256 IP addresses each).
      <ulink type="block"
      url="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1918.html"/></para>
    </sidebar>

    <para>The gateway can also perform two kinds of <emphasis>network
    address translation</emphasis> (or NAT for short). The first kind,
    <emphasis>Destination NAT</emphasis> (DNAT) is a technique to alter the
    destination IP address (and/or the TCP or UDP port) for a (generally)
    incoming connection. The connection tracking mechanism also alters the
    following packets in the same connection to ensure continuity in the
    communication. The second kind of NAT is <emphasis>Source
    NAT</emphasis> (SNAT), of which <emphasis>masquerading</emphasis> is a
    particular case; SNAT alters the source IP address (and/or the TCP or
    UDP port) of a (generally) outgoing connection. As for DNAT, all the
    packets in the connection are appropriately handled by the connection
    tracking mechanism. Note that NAT is only relevant for IPv4 and its
    limited address space; in IPv6, the wide availability of addresses
    greatly reduces the usefulness of NAT by allowing all “internal”
    addresses to be directly routable on the Internet (this does not imply
    that internal machines are accessible, since intermediary firewalls can
    filter traffic).</para>
    <indexterm><primary>NAT</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Network</primary><secondary>Address Translation</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>SNAT</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>DNAT</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Destination NAT</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Source NAT</primary></indexterm>

    <sidebar>
      <title><emphasis>BACK TO BASICS</emphasis> Port forwarding</title>
      <indexterm><primary>port forwarding</primary></indexterm>

      <para>A concrete application of DNAT is <emphasis>port
      forwarding</emphasis>. Incoming connections to a given port of a
      machine are forwarded to a port on another machine. Other solutions
      may exist for achieving a similar effect, though, especially at the
      application level with <command>ssh</command> (see <xref
      linkend="section.ssh-port-forwarding"/>) or
      <command>redir</command>.</para>
    </sidebar>

    <para>Enough theory, let's get practical. Turning a Debian system into
    a gateway is a simple matter of enabling the appropriate option in the
    Linux kernel, by way of the <filename>/proc/</filename> virtual
    filesystem:</para>

    <screen>
<computeroutput># </computeroutput><userinput>echo 1 &gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/default/forwarding</userinput>
</screen>

    <para>This option can also be automatically enabled on boot if
    <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> sets the
    <literal>net.ipv4.conf.default.forwarding</literal> option to
    <literal>1</literal>.</para>

    <example id="example.sysctl.conf">
      <title>The <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename> file</title>

      <programlisting>
net.ipv4.conf.default.forwarding = 1
net.ipv4.conf.default.rp_filter = 1
net.ipv4.tcp_syncookies = 1
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>The same effect can be obtained for IPv6 by simply replacing
    <literal>ipv4</literal> with <literal>ipv6</literal> in the manual
    command and using the <literal>net.ipv6.conf.all.forwarding</literal>
    line in <filename>/etc/sysctl.conf</filename>.</para>

    <para>Enabling IPv4 masquerading is a slightly more complex operation
    that involves configuring the <emphasis>netfilter</emphasis>
    firewall.</para>

    <para>Similarly, using NAT (for IPv4) requires configuring
    <emphasis>netfilter</emphasis>. Since the primary purpose of this
    component is packet filtering, the details are listed in <xref
    linkend="security" xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle nopage"/> (see
    <xref linkend="sect.firewall-packet-filtering"/>).</para>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.virtual-private-network">
    <title>Virtual Private Network</title>

    <para>A <emphasis>Virtual Private Network</emphasis> (VPN for short) is
    a way to link two different local networks through the Internet by way
    of a tunnel; the tunnel is usually encrypted for confidentiality. VPNs
    are often used to integrate a remote machine within a company's local
    network.</para>
    <indexterm><primary>network</primary><secondary>virtual private</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>VPN</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>virtual private network</primary></indexterm>

    <para>Several tools provide this. OpenVPN is an efficient solution,
    easy to deploy and maintain, based on SSL/TLS. Another possibility is
    using IPsec to encrypt IP traffic between two machines; this encryption
    is transparent, which means that applications running on these hosts
    need not be modified to take the VPN into account. SSH can also be used
    to provide a VPN, in addition to its more conventional features.
    Finally, a VPN can be established using Microsoft's PPTP protocol.
    Other solutions exist, but are beyond the focus of this book.</para>
    <section id="section.openvpn">
      <title>OpenVPN</title>
      <indexterm><primary>OpenVPN</primary></indexterm>

      <para>OpenVPN is a piece of software dedicated to creating virtual
      private networks. Its setup involves creating virtual network
      interfaces on the VPN server and on the client(s); both
      <literal>tun</literal> (for IP-level tunnels) and
      <literal>tap</literal> (for Ethernet-level tunnels) interfaces are
      supported. In practice, <literal>tun</literal> interfaces will most
      often be used except when the VPN clients are meant to be integrated
      into the server's local network by way of an Ethernet bridge.</para>

      <para>OpenVPN relies on OpenSSL for all the SSL/TLS cryptography and
      associated features (confidentiality, authentication, integrity,
      non-repudiation). It can be configured either with a shared private
      key or using X.509 certificates based on a public key infrastructure.
      The latter configuration is strongly preferred since it allows
      greater flexibility when faced with a growing number of roaming users
      accessing the VPN.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>CULTURE</emphasis> SSL and TLS</title>
        <indexterm><primary>SSL</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>TLS</primary></indexterm>

	<para>The SSL protocol (<emphasis>Secure Socket Layer</emphasis>)
	was invented by Netscape to secure connections to web servers. It
	was later standardized by IETF under the acronym TLS
	(<emphasis>Transport Layer Security</emphasis>); TLS is very
	similar to SSLv3 with only a few fixes and improvements.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <section id="sect.easy-rsa">
        <title>Public Key Infrastructure: <emphasis>easy-rsa</emphasis></title>
        <indexterm><primary>PKI (Public Key Infrastructure)</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>Public Key Infrastructure</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>X.509, certificate</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>certificate</primary><secondary>X.509</secondary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary><emphasis>easy-rsa</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>RSA (algorithm)</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>key pair</primary></indexterm>

	<para>The RSA algorithm is widely used in public-key cryptography.
	It involves a “key pair”, comprised of a private and a public
	key. The two keys are closely linked to each other, and their
	mathematical properties are such that a message encrypted with the
	public key can only be decrypted by someone knowing the private
	key, which ensures confidentiality. In the opposite direction, a
	message encrypted with the private key can be decrypted by anyone
	knowing the public key, which allows authenticating the origin of a
	message since only someone with access to the private key could
	generate it. When associated with a digital hash function (MD5,
	SHA1, or a more recent variant), this leads to a signature
	mechanism that can be applied to any message.</para>

	<para>However, anyone can create a key pair, store any identity on
	it, and pretend to be the identity of their choice. One solution
	involves the concept of a <emphasis>Certification
	Authority</emphasis> (CA), formalized by the X.509 standard. This
	term covers an entity that holds a trusted key pair known as a
	<emphasis>root certificate</emphasis>. This certificate is only
	used to sign other certificates (key pairs), after proper steps
	have been undertaken to check the identity stored on the key pair.
	Applications using X.509 can then check the certificates presented
	to them, if they know about the trusted root certificates.</para>

	<para>OpenVPN follows this rule. Since public CAs only emit
	certificates in exchange for a (hefty) fee, it is also possible to
	create a private certification authority within the company. For
	that purpose, OpenVPN provides the <emphasis>easy-rsa</emphasis>
	tool which serves as an X.509 certification infrastructure. Its
	implementation is a set of scripts using the
	<command>openssl</command> command; these scripts can be found
	under
	<filename>/usr/share/doc/openvpn/examples/easy-rsa/2.0/</filename>.</para>

	<para>The Falcot Corp administrators use this tool to create the
	required certificates, both for the server and the clients. This
	allows the configuration of all clients to be similar since they
	will only have to be set up so as to trust certificates coming from
	Falcot's local CA. This CA is the first certificate to create; to
	this end, the administrators copy the directory containing
	<emphasis>easy-rsa</emphasis> into a more appropriate location,
	preferably on a machine not connected to the network in order to
	mitigate the risk of the CA's private key being stolen.</para>

        <screen>
<computeroutput>$ </computeroutput><userinput>cp -r /usr/share/doc/openvpn/examples/easy-rsa/2.0 pki-falcot
</userinput><computeroutput>$ </computeroutput><userinput>cd pki-falcot</userinput>
</screen>

	<para>They then store the required parameters into the
	<filename>vars</filename> file, especially those named with a
	<literal>KEY_</literal> prefix; these variables are then integrated
	into the environment:</para>

        <screen>
<computeroutput>$ </computeroutput><userinput>vim vars
</userinput><computeroutput>$ </computeroutput><userinput>grep KEY_ vars
</userinput><computeroutput>export KEY_CONFIG=`$EASY_RSA/whichopensslcnf $EASY_RSA`
export KEY_DIR="$EASY_RSA/keys"
echo NOTE: If you run ./clean-all, I will be doing a rm -rf on $KEY_DIR
export KEY_SIZE=1024
export KEY_EXPIRE=3650
export KEY_COUNTRY="FR"
export KEY_PROVINCE="Loire"
export KEY_CITY="Saint-Étienne"
export KEY_ORG="Falcot Corp"
export KEY_EMAIL="admin@falcot.com"
$ </computeroutput><userinput>. ./vars
</userinput><computeroutput>NOTE: If you run ./clean-all, I will be doing a rm -rf on /home/rhertzog/pki-falcot/keys
$ </computeroutput><userinput>./clean-all
</userinput>
</screen>

	<para>The next step is the creation of the CA's key pair itself
	(the two parts of the key pair will be stored under
	<filename>keys/ca.crt</filename> and
	<filename>keys/ca.key</filename> during this step):</para>

        <screen>
<computeroutput>$ </computeroutput><userinput>./build-ca</userinput>
<computeroutput>Generating a 1024 bit RSA private key
..............................................++++++
.......................++++++
writing new private key to 'ca.key'
-----
You are about to be asked to enter information that will be incorporated
into your certificate request.
What you are about to enter is what is called a Distinguished Name or a DN.
There are quite a few fields but you can leave some blank
For some fields there will be a default value,
If you enter '.', the field will be left blank.
-----
Country Name (2 letter code) [FR]:
State or Province Name (full name) [Loire]:
Locality Name (eg, city) [Saint-Étienne]:
Organization Name (eg, company) [Falcot Corp]:
Organizational Unit Name (eg, section) []:
Common Name (eg, your name or your server's hostname) [Falcot Corp CA]:
Name []:
Email Address [admin@falcot.com]:
</computeroutput>
</screen>

	<para>The certificate for the VPN server can now be created, as
	well as the Diffie-Hellman parameters required for the server side
	of an SSL/TLS connection. The VPN server is identified by its DNS
	name <literal>vpn.falcot.com</literal>; this name is re-used for
	the generated key files
	(<filename>keys/vpn.falcot.com.crt</filename> for the public
	certificate, <filename>keys/vpn.falcot.com.key</filename>for the
	private key):</para>

        <screen>
<computeroutput>$ </computeroutput><userinput>./build-key-server vpn.falcot.com
</userinput><computeroutput>Generating a 1024 bit RSA private key
...............++++++
...........++++++
writing new private key to 'vpn.falcot.com.key'
-----
You are about to be asked to enter information that will be incorporated
into your certificate request.
What you are about to enter is what is called a Distinguished Name or a DN.
There are quite a few fields but you can leave some blank
For some fields there will be a default value,
If you enter '.', the field will be left blank.
-----
Country Name (2 letter code) [FR]:
State or Province Name (full name) [Loire]:
Locality Name (eg, city) [Saint-Étienne]:
Organization Name (eg, company) [Falcot Corp]:
Organizational Unit Name (eg, section) []:
Common Name (eg, your name or your server's hostname) [vpn.falcot.com]:
Name []:
Email Address [admin@falcot.com]:

Please enter the following 'extra' attributes
to be sent with your certificate request
A challenge password []:
An optional company name []:
Using configuration from /home/rhertzog/pki-falcot/openssl.cnf
Check that the request matches the signature
Signature ok
The Subject's Distinguished Name is as follows
countryName           :PRINTABLE:'FR'
stateOrProvinceName   :PRINTABLE:'Loire'
localityName          :T61STRING:'Saint-\0xFFFFFFC3\0xFFFFFF89tienne'
organizationName      :PRINTABLE:'Falcot Corp'
commonName            :PRINTABLE:'vpn.falcot.com'
emailAddress          :IA5STRING:'admin@falcot.com'
Certificate is to be certified until Oct  9 13:57:42 2020 GMT (3650 days)
Sign the certificate? [y/n]:</computeroutput><userinput>y
</userinput><computeroutput>

1 out of 1 certificate requests certified, commit? [y/n]</computeroutput><userinput>y
</userinput><computeroutput>Write out database with 1 new entries
Data Base Updated
$ </computeroutput><userinput>./build-dh
</userinput><computeroutput>Generating DH parameters, 1024 bit long safe prime, generator 2
This is going to take a long time
..............+.......+.................................++*++*++*
</computeroutput>
</screen>

	<para>The following step creates certificates for the VPN clients;
	one certificate is required for each computer or person allowed to
	use the VPN:</para>

        <screen>
<computeroutput>$ </computeroutput><userinput>./build-key JoeSmith
</userinput><computeroutput>Generating a 1024 bit RSA private key
................++++++
.............................++++++
writing new private key to 'JoeSmith.key'
-----
You are about to be asked to enter information that will be incorporated
into your certificate request.
What you are about to enter is what is called a Distinguished Name or a DN.
There are quite a few fields but you can leave some blank
For some fields there will be a default value,
If you enter '.', the field will be left blank.
-----
Country Name (2 letter code) [FR]:
State or Province Name (full name) [Loire]:
Locality Name (eg, city) [Saint-Étienne]:
Organization Name (eg, company) [Falcot Corp]:
Organizational Unit Name (eg, section) []:
Common Name (eg, your name or your server's hostname) [JoeSmith]:</computeroutput><userinput>Joe Smith
</userinput><computeroutput>Name []:
Email Address [admin@falcot.com]:</computeroutput><userinput>joe@falcot.com
</userinput><computeroutput>[…]</computeroutput></screen>

	<para>Now all certificates have been created, they need to be
	copied where appropriate: the root certificate's public key
	(<filename>keys/ca.crt</filename>) will be stored on all machines
	(both server and clients) as
	<filename>/etc/ssl/certs/Falcot_CA.crt</filename>. The server's
	certificate is installed only on the server
	(<filename>keys/vpn.falcot.com.crt</filename> goes to
	<filename>/etc/ssl/vpn.falcot.com.crt</filename>, and
	<filename>keys/vpn.falcot.com.key</filename> goes to
	<filename>/etc/ssl/private/vpn.falcot.com.key</filename> with
	restricted permissions so that only the administrator can read it),
	with the corresponding Diffie-Hellman parameters
	(<filename>keys/dh1024.pem</filename>) installed to
	<filename>/etc/openvpn/dh1024.pem</filename>. Client certificates
	are installed on the corresponding VPN client in a similar
	fashion.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Configuring the OpenVPN Server</title>

	<para>By default, the OpenVPN initialization script tries starting
	all virtual private networks defined in
	<filename>/etc/openvpn/*.conf</filename>. Setting up a VPN server
	is therefore a matter of storing a corresponding configuration file
	in this directory. A good starting point is
	<filename>/usr/share/doc/openvpn/examples/sample-config-files/server.conf.gz</filename>,
	which leads to a rather standard server. Of course, some parameters
	need to be adapted: <literal>ca</literal>, <literal>cert</literal>,
	<literal>key</literal> and <literal>dh</literal> need to describe
	the selected locations (respectively,
	<literal>/etc/ssl/certs/Falcot_CA.crt</literal>,
	<literal>/etc/ssl/vpn.falcot.com.crt</literal>,
	<literal>/etc/ssl/private/vpn.falcot.com.key</literal> and
	<literal>/etc/openvpn/dh1024.pem</literal>). The <literal>server
	10.8.0.0 255.255.255.0</literal> directive defines the subnet to be
	used by the VPN; the server uses the first IP address in that range
	(<literal>10.8.0.1</literal>) and the rest of the addresses are
	allocated to clients.</para>

	<para>With this configuration, starting OpenVPN creates the virtual
	network interface, usually under the <literal>tun0</literal> name.
	However, firewalls are often configured at the same time as the
	real network interfaces, which happens before OpenVPN starts. Good
	practice therefore recommends creating a persistent virtual network
	interface, and configuring OpenVPN to use this pre-existing
	interface. This further allows choosing the name for this
	interface. To this end, <command>openvpn --mktun --dev vpn
	--dev-type tun</command> creates a virtual network interface named
	<literal>vpn</literal> with type <literal>tun</literal>; this
	command can easily be integrated in the firewall configuration
	script, or in an <literal>up</literal> directive of the
	<filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename> file. The OpenVPN
	configuration file must also be updated accordingly, with the
	<literal>dev vpn</literal> and <literal>dev-type tun</literal>
	directives.</para>

	<para>Barring further action, VPN clients can only access the VPN
	server itself by way of the <literal>10.8.0.1</literal> address.
	Granting the clients access to the local network (192.168.0.0/24),
	requires adding a <literal>push route 192.168.0.0
	255.255.255.0</literal> directive to the OpenVPN configuration so
	that VPN clients automatically get a network route telling them
	that this network is reachable by way of the VPN. Furthermore,
	machines on the local network also need to be informed that the
	route to the VPN goes through the VPN server (this automatically
	works when the VPN server is installed on the gateway).
	Alternatively, the VPN server can be configured to perform IP
	masquerading so that connections coming from VPN clients appear as
	if they are coming from the VPN server instead (see <xref
	linkend="sect.gateway"/>).</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Configuring the OpenVPN Client</title>

	<para>Setting up an OpenVPN client also requires creating a
	configuration file in <filename>/etc/openvpn/</filename>. A
	standard configuration can be obtained by using
	<filename>/usr/share/doc/openvpn/examples/sample-config-files/client.conf</filename>
	as a starting point. The <literal>remote vpn.falcot.com
	1194</literal> directive describes the address and port of the
	OpenVPN server; the <literal>ca</literal>, <literal>cert</literal>
	and <literal>key</literal> also need to be adapted to describe the
	locations of the key files.</para>

	<para>If the VPN should not be started automatically on boot, set
	the <literal>AUTOSTART</literal> directive to
	<literal>none</literal> in the
	<filename>/etc/default/openvpn</filename> file. Starting or
	stopping a given VPN connection is always possible with the
	commands <command>/etc/init.d/openpvn start
	<replaceable>name</replaceable></command> and
	<command>/etc/init.d/openpvn stop
	<replaceable>name</replaceable></command> (where the connection
	<replaceable>name</replaceable> matches the one defined in
	<filename>/etc/openvpn/<replaceable>name</replaceable>.conf</filename>).</para>

	<para>The <emphasis
	role="pkg">network-manager-openvpn-gnome</emphasis> package
	contains an extension to Network Manager (see <xref
	linkend="sect.config-reseau-itinerante"/>) that allows managing
	OpenVPN virtual private networks. This allows every user to
	configure OpenVPN connections graphically and to control them from
	the network management icon. <indexterm><primary><emphasis
	role="pkg">network-manager-openvpn-gnome</emphasis></primary></indexterm></para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="section.ssh-vpn">
      <title>Virtual Private Network with SSH</title>
      <indexterm><primary>SSH</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>PPP</primary></indexterm>

      <para>There are actually two ways of creating a virtual private
      network with SSH. The historic one involves establishing a PPP layer
      over the SSH link. This method is described in a HOWTO document:
      <ulink type="block" url="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/ppp-ssh/"/></para>

      <para>The second method is more recent, and was introduced with
      OpenSSH 4.3; it is now possible for OpenSSH to create virtual
      network interfaces (<literal>tun*</literal>) on both sides of an SSH
      connection, and these virtual interfaces can be configured exactly as
      if they were physical interfaces. The tunneling system must first be
      enabled by setting <literal>PermitTunnel</literal> to “yes” in
      the SSH server configuration file
      (<filename>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</filename>). When establishing the
      SSH connection, the creation of a tunnel must be explicitly requested
      with the <literal>-w any:any</literal> option (<literal>any</literal>
      can be replaced with the desired <literal>tun</literal> device
      number). This requires the user to have administrator privilege on
      both sides, so as to be able to create the network device (in other
      words, the connection must be established as root).</para>

      <para>Both methods for creating a virtual private network over SSH
      are quite straightforward. However, the VPN they provide is not the
      most efficient available; in particular, it does not handle high
      levels of traffic very well.</para>

      <para>The explanation is that when a TCP/IP stack is encapsulated
      within a TCP/IP connection (for SSH), the TCP protocol is used twice,
      once for the SSH connection and once within the tunnel. This
      leads to problems, especially due to the way TCP adapts to network
      conditions by altering timeout delays. The following site describes
      the problem in more detail: <ulink type="block"
      url="http://sites.inka.de/sites/bigred/devel/tcp-tcp.html"/> VPNs
      over SSH should therefore be restricted to one-off tunnels with no
      performance constraints.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="section.ipsec">
      <title>IPsec</title>
      <indexterm><primary>IPsec</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>openswan</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>strongswan</command></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>racoon</command></primary></indexterm>

      <para>IPsec, despite being the standard in IP VPNs, is rather more
      involved in its implementation. The IPsec engine itself is integrated
      in the Linux kernel; the required user-space parts, the control and
      configuration tools, are provided by the <emphasis
      role="pkg">ipsec-tools</emphasis> package. In concrete terms, each
      host's <filename>/etc/ipsec-tools.conf</filename> contains the
      parameters for <emphasis>IPsec tunnels</emphasis> (or
      <emphasis>Security Associations</emphasis>, in the IPsec terminology)
      that the host is concerned with;
      <command>/etc/init.d/setkey</command> script provides a way to start
      and stop a tunnel (each tunnel is a secure link to another host
      connected to the virtual private network). This file can be built by
      hand from the documentation provided by the
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>setkey</refentrytitle>
      <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> manual page. However,
      explicitly writing the parameters for all hosts in a non-trivial set
      of machines quickly becomes an arduous task, since the number of
      tunnels grows fast. Installing an IKE daemon (for <emphasis>IPsec Key
      Exchange</emphasis>) such as <emphasis role="pkg">racoon</emphasis>,
      <emphasis role="pkg">strongswan</emphasis> or <emphasis
      role="pkg">openswan</emphasis> makes the process much simpler by
      bringing administration together at a central point, and more secure
      by rotating the keys periodically.
      <indexterm><primary>IKE</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>IPsec</primary><secondary>IPsec Key
      Exchange</secondary></indexterm> <indexterm><primary>key
      pair</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>setkey</command></primary></indexterm></para>

      <para>In spite of its status as the reference, the complexity of
      setting up IPsec restricts its usage in practice. OpenVPN-based
      solutions will generally be preferred when the required tunnels are
      neither too many nor too dynamic.</para>

      <sidebar role="important">
        <title><emphasis>CAUTION</emphasis> IPsec and NAT</title>

	<para>NATing firewalls and IPsec do not work well together: since
	IPsec signs the packets, any change on these packets that the
	firewall might perform will void the signature, and the packets
	will be rejected at their destination. Various IPsec
	implementations now include the <emphasis>NAT-T</emphasis>
	technique (for <emphasis>NAT Traversal</emphasis>), which basically
	encapsulates the IPsec packet within a standard UDP packet.</para>
        <indexterm><primary>NAT-T</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>NAT Traversal</primary></indexterm>
      </sidebar>

      <sidebar role="fil">
        <title><emphasis>SECURITY</emphasis> IPsec and firewalls</title>

	<para>The standard mode of operation of IPsec involves data
	exchanges on UDP port 500 for key exchanges (also on UDP
	port 4500 if case NAT-T is in use). Moreover, IPsec packets use
	two dedicated IP protocols that the firewall must let through;
	reception of these packets is based on their protocol numbers, 50
	(ESP) and 51 (AH).</para>
        <indexterm><primary>ESP, protocol</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>AH, protocol</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>protocol</primary><secondary>AH</secondary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>protocol</primary><secondary>ESP</secondary></indexterm>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
    <section id="section.pptp">
      <title>PPTP</title>

      <para>PPTP (for <emphasis>Point-to-Point Tunneling
      Protocol</emphasis>) uses two communication channels, one for control
      data and one for payload data; the latter uses the GRE protocol
      (<emphasis>Generic Routing Encapsulation</emphasis>). A standard PPP
      link is then set up over the data exchange channel.</para>
      <indexterm><primary>PPTP</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>Point-to-Point Tunneling Protocol</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>GRE, protocol</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>protocol</primary><secondary>GRE</secondary></indexterm>
      <section id="section.pptp-config-client">
        <title>Configuring the Client</title>

	<para>The <emphasis role="pkg">pptp-linux</emphasis> package
	contains an easily-configured PPTP client for Linux. The following
	instructions take their inspiration from the official
	documentation: <ulink type="block"
	url="http://pptpclient.sourceforge.net/howto-debian.phtml"/></para>
        <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">pptp-linux</emphasis></primary></indexterm>

	<para>The Falcot administrators created several files:
	<filename>/etc/ppp/options.pptp</filename>,
	<filename>/etc/ppp/peers/falcot</filename>,
	<filename>/etc/ppp/ip-up.d/falcot</filename>, and
	<filename>/etc/ppp/ip-down.d/falcot</filename>.</para>

        <example id="example.ppp-options.pptp">
          <title>The <filename>/etc/ppp/options.pptp</filename> file</title>

          <programlisting>
# PPP options used for a PPTP connection
lock
noauth
nobsdcomp
nodeflate
</programlisting>
        </example>

        <example id="example.ppp-peers-falcot">
          <title>The <filename>/etc/ppp/peers/falcot</filename> file</title>

          <programlisting>
# vpn.falcot.com is the PPTP server
pty "pptp vpn.falcot.com --nolaunchpppd"
# the connection will identify as the "vpn" user
user vpn
remotename pptp
# encryption is needed
require-mppe-128
file /etc/ppp/options.pptp
ipparam falcot
</programlisting>
        </example>

        <example id="example.ppp-ip-up.d-falcot">
          <title>The <filename>/etc/ppp/ip-up.d/falcot</filename> file</title>

          <programlisting>
# Create the route to the Falcot network
if [ "$6" = "falcot" ]; then
  # 192.168.0.0/24 is the (remote) Falcot network
  route add -net 192.168.0.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 dev $1
fi
</programlisting>
        </example>

        <example id="example.ppp-ip-down.d-falcot">
          <title>The <filename>/etc/ppp/ip-down.d/falcot</filename> file</title>

          <programlisting>
# Delete the route to the Falcot network
if [ "$6" = "falcot" ]; then
  # 192.168.0.0/24 is the (remote) Falcot network
  route del -net 192.168.0.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 dev $1
fi
</programlisting>
        </example>

        <sidebar role="fil">
          <title><emphasis>SECURITY</emphasis> MPPE</title>

	  <para>Securing PPTP involves using the MPPE feature
	  (<emphasis>Microsoft Point-to-Point Encryption</emphasis>), which
	  is available in official Debian kernels as a module.</para>
          <indexterm><primary>MPPE</primary></indexterm>
          <indexterm><primary>Microsoft</primary><secondary>Point-to-Point Encryption</secondary></indexterm>
        </sidebar>
      </section>
      <section id="section.pptp-config-serveur">
        <title>Configuring the Server</title>

        <sidebar role="important">
          <title><emphasis>CAUTION</emphasis> PPTP and firewalls</title>

	  <para>Intermediate firewalls need to be configured to let through
	  IP packets using protocol 47 (GRE). Moreover, the PPTP server's
	  port 1723 needs to be open so that the communication channel can
	  happen.</para>
        </sidebar>

	<para><command>pptpd</command> is the PPTP server for Linux. Its
	main configuration file, <filename>/etc/pptpd.conf</filename>,
	requires very few changes: <emphasis>localip</emphasis> (local IP
	address) and <emphasis>remoteip</emphasis> (remote IP address). In
	the example below, the PPTP server always uses the
	<literal>192.168.0.199</literal> address, and PPTP clients receive
	IP addresses from <literal>192.168.0.200</literal> to
	<literal>192.168.0.250</literal>.</para>

        <example id="example.pptpd.conf">
          <title>The <filename>/etc/pptpd.conf</filename> file</title>

          <programlisting>
# TAG: speed
#
#       Specifies the speed for the PPP daemon to talk at.
#
speed 115200

# TAG: option
#
#       Specifies the location of the PPP options file.
#       By default PPP looks in '/etc/ppp/options'
#
option /etc/ppp/pptpd-options

# TAG: debug
#
#       Turns on (more) debugging to syslog
#
# debug

# TAG: localip
# TAG: remoteip
#
#       Specifies the local and remote IP address ranges.
#
#       You can specify single IP addresses separated by commas or you can
#       specify ranges, or both. For example:
#
#               192.168.0.234,192.168.0.245-249,192.168.0.254
#
#       IMPORTANT RESTRICTIONS:
#
#       1. No spaces are permitted between commas or within addresses.
#
#       2. If you give more IP addresses than MAX_CONNECTIONS, it will
#          start at the beginning of the list and go until it gets
#          MAX_CONNECTIONS IPs. Others will be ignored.
#
#       3. No shortcuts in ranges! ie. 234-8 does not mean 234 to 238,
#          you must type 234-238 if you mean this.
#
#       4. If you give a single localIP, that's ok - all local IPs will
#          be set to the given one. You MUST still give at least one remote
#          IP for each simultaneous client.
#
#localip 192.168.0.234-238,192.168.0.245
#remoteip 192.168.1.234-238,192.168.1.245
#localip 10.0.1.1
#remoteip 10.0.1.2-100
localip 192.168.0.199
remoteip 192.168.0.200-250
</programlisting>
        </example>

	<para>The PPP configuration used by the PPTP server also requires a
	few changes in <filename>/etc/ppp/pptpd-options</filename>. The
	important parameters are the server name (<literal>pptp</literal>),
	the domain name (<literal>falcot.com</literal>), and the IP
	addresses for DNS and WINS servers.</para>

        <example id="example.ppp-pptpd-options">
          <title>The <filename>/etc/ppp/pptpd-options</filename> file</title>

          <programlisting>
## turn pppd syslog debugging on
#debug

## change 'servername' to whatever you specify as your server name in chap-secrets
name pptp
## change the domainname to your local domain
domain falcot.com

## these are reasonable defaults for WinXXXX clients
## for the security related settings
# The Debian pppd package now supports both MSCHAP and MPPE, so enable them
# here. Please note that the kernel support for MPPE must also be present!
auth
require-chap
require-mschap
require-mschap-v2
require-mppe-128

## Fill in your addresses
ms-dns 192.168.0.1
ms-wins 192.168.0.1

## Fill in your netmask
netmask 255.255.255.0

## some defaults
nodefaultroute
proxyarp
lock
</programlisting>
        </example>

	<para>The last step involves registering the <literal>vpn</literal>
	user (and the associated password) in the
	<filename>/etc/ppp/chap-secrets</filename> file. Contrary to other
	instances where an asterisk (<literal>*</literal>) would work, the
	server name must be filled explicitly here. Furthermore, Windows
	PPTP clients identify themselves under the
	<literal><replaceable>DOMAIN</replaceable>\\<replaceable>USER</replaceable></literal>
	form, instead of only providing a user name. This explains why the
	file also mentions the <literal>FALCOT\\vpn</literal> user. It is
	also possible to specify individual IP addresses for users; an
	asterisk in this field specifies that dynamic addressing should be
	used.</para>

        <example id="example.ppp-chap-secrets">
          <title>The <filename>/etc/ppp/chap-secrets</filename> file</title>

          <programlisting>
# Secrets for authentication using CHAP
# client        server  secret      IP addresses
vpn             pptp    f@Lc3au     *
FALCOT\\vpn     pptp    f@Lc3au     *
</programlisting>
        </example>

        <sidebar role="important">
          <title><emphasis>SECURITY</emphasis> PPTP vulnerabilities</title>

	  <para>Microsoft's first PPTP implementation drew severe criticism
	  because it had many security vulnerabilities; most have since
	  then been fixed in more recent versions. The configuration
	  documented in this section uses the latest version of the
	  protocol. Be aware though that removing some options (such as
	  <literal>require-mppe-128</literal> and
	  <literal>require-mschap-v2</literal>) would make the service
	  vulnerable again.</para>
        </sidebar>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.quality-of-service">
    <title>Quality of Service</title>
    <section id="section.qos-principe">
      <title>Principle and Mechanism</title>

      <para><emphasis>Quality of Service</emphasis> (or
      <emphasis>QoS</emphasis> for short) refers to a set of techniques
      that guarantee or improve the quality of the service provided to
      applications. The most popular such technique involves classifying
      the network traffic into categories, and differentiating the handling
      of traffic according to which category it belongs to. The main
      application of this differentiated services concept is
      <emphasis>traffic shaping</emphasis>, which limits the data
      transmission rates for connections related to some services and/or
      hosts so as not to saturate the available bandwidth and starve
      important other services. Traffic shaping is a particularly good fit
      for TCP traffic, since this protocol automatically adapts to
      available bandwidth.</para>
      <indexterm><primary>QoS</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>quality of service</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>quality</primary><secondary>of service</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>service</primary><secondary>quality</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>It is also possible to alter the priorities on traffic, which
      allows prioritizing packets related to interactive services (such as
      <command>ssh</command> and <command>telnet</command>) or to services
      that only deal with small blocks of data.</para>

      <para>The Debian kernels include the features required for QoS along
      with their associated modules. These modules are many, and each of
      them provides a different service, most notably by way of special
      schedulers for the queues of IP packets; the wide range of available
      scheduler behaviors spans the whole range of possible
      requirements.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>CULTURE</emphasis> LARTC — <emphasis>Linux Advanced Routing &amp; Traffic Control</emphasis></title>

	<para>The <emphasis>Linux Advanced Routing &amp; Traffic
	Control</emphasis> HOWTO is the reference document covering
	everything there is to know about network quality of service.
	<ulink type="block" url="http://www.lartc.org/howto/"/></para>
        <indexterm><primary>routing</primary><secondary>advanced</secondary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>traffic control</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>control, of traffic</primary></indexterm>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
    <section id="section.qos-config">
      <title>Configuring and Implementing</title>

      <para>QoS parameters are set through the <command>tc</command>
      command (provided by the <emphasis role="pkg">iproute</emphasis>
      package). Since its interface is quite complex, using higher-level
      tools is recommended.</para>
      <indexterm><primary><emphasis>iproute</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>tc</command></primary></indexterm>
      <section id="section.qos-wondershaper">
        <title>Reducing Latencies: <command>wondershaper</command></title>

	<para>The main purpose of <command>wondershaper</command> (in the
	similarly-named package) is to minimize latencies independent of
	network load. This is achieved by limiting total traffic to a value
	that falls just short of the link saturation value.</para>
        <indexterm><primary><command>wondershaper</command></primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>limitation, of traffic</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>traffic</primary><secondary>limitation</secondary></indexterm>

	<para>Once a network interface is configured, setting up this
	traffic limitation is achieved by running <command>wondershaper
	<replaceable>interface</replaceable>
	<replaceable>download_rate</replaceable>
	<replaceable>upload_rate</replaceable></command>. The interface can
	be <literal>eth0</literal> or <literal>ppp0</literal> for example,
	and both rates are expressed in kilobits per second. The
	<command>wondershaper remove
	<replaceable>interface</replaceable></command> command disables
	traffic control on the specified interface.</para>

	<para>For an Ethernet connection, this script is best called right
	after the interface is configured. This is done by adding
	<literal>up</literal> and <literal>down</literal> directives to the
	<filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename> file allowing declared
	commands to be run, respectively, after the interface is configured
	and before it is deconfigured. For example:</para>

        <example id="example.network-interfaces">
          <title>Changes in the <filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename> file</title>

          <programlisting>
iface eth0 inet dhcp
    up /sbin/wondershaper eth0 500 100
    down /sbin/wondershaper remove eth0
</programlisting>
        </example>

	<para>In the PPP case, creating a script that calls
	<command>wondershaper</command> in
	<filename>/etc/ppp/ip-up.d/</filename> will enable traffic control
	as soon as the connection is up.</para>

        <sidebar role="fil">
          <title><emphasis>GOING FURTHER</emphasis> Optimal configuration</title>

	  <para>The
	  <filename>/usr/share/doc/wondershaper/README.Debian.gz</filename>
	  file describes, in some detail, the configuration method
	  recommended by the package maintainer. In particular, it advises
	  measuring the download and upload speeds so as to best evaluate
	  real limits.</para>
        </sidebar>
      </section>
      <section id="section.qos-config-standard">
        <title>Standard Configuration</title>

	<para>Barring a specific QoS configuration, the Linux kernel uses
	the <literal>pfifo_fast</literal> queue scheduler, which provides a
	few interesting features by itself. The priority of each processed
	IP packet is based on the ToS field (<emphasis>Type of
	Service</emphasis>) of this packet; modifying this field is enough
	to take advantage of the scheduling features. There are five
	possible values:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
	    <para>Normal-Service (0);</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>Minimize-Cost (2);</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>Maximize-Reliability (4);</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>Maximize-Throughput (8);</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    <para>Minimize-Delay (16).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <indexterm><primary>ToS</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>Type of Service</primary></indexterm>

	<para>The ToS field can be set by applications that generate IP
	packets, or modified on the fly by <emphasis>netfilter</emphasis>.
	The following rules are sufficient to increase responsiveness for a
	server's SSH service:</para>

        <programlisting role="scale">
iptables -t mangle -A PREROUTING -p tcp --sport ssh -j TOS --set-tos Minimize-Delay
iptables -t mangle -A PREROUTING -p tcp --dport ssh -j TOS --set-tos Minimize-Delay
</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.dynamic-routing">
    <title>Dynamic Routing</title>
    <indexterm><primary>routing</primary><secondary>dynamic</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>quagga</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>zebra</command></primary></indexterm>

    <para>The reference tool for dynamic routing is currently
    <command>quagga</command>, from the similarly-named package; it used to
    be <command>zebra</command> until development of the latter stopped.
    However, <command>quagga</command> kept the names of the programs for
    compatibility reasons which explains the <command>zebra</command>
    commands below.</para>

    <sidebar role="fil">
      <title><emphasis>BACK TO BASICS</emphasis> Dynamic routing</title>

      <para>Dynamic routing allows routers to adjust, in real time, the
      paths used for transmitting IP packets. Each protocol involves its
      own method of defining routes (shortest path, use routes advertised
      by peers, and so on).</para>

      <para>In the Linux kernel, a route links a network device to a set of
      machines that can be reached through this device. The
      <command>route</command> command defines new routes and displays
      existing ones.</para>
      <indexterm><primary><command>route</command></primary></indexterm>
    </sidebar>

    <para>Quagga is a set of daemons cooperating to define the routing
    tables to be used by the Linux kernel; each routing protocol (most
    notably BGP, OSPF and RIP) provides its own daemon. The
    <command>zebra</command> daemon collects information from other daemons
    and handles static routing tables accordingly. The other daemons are
    known as <command>bgpd</command>, <command>ospfd</command>,
    <command>ospf6d</command>, <command>ripd</command>, and
    <command>ripngd</command>.</para>
    <indexterm><primary>OSPF</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>BGP</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>RIP</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>bgpd</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>ospfd</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>ospf6d</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>ripd</command></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><command>ripngd</command></primary></indexterm>

    <para>Daemons are enabled by editing the
    <filename>/etc/quagga/daemons</filename> file and creating the
    appropriate configuration file in <filename>/etc/quagga/</filename>;
    this configuration file must be named after the daemon, with a
    <filename>.conf</filename> extension, and belong to the
    <literal>quagga</literal> user and the <literal>quaggavty</literal>
    group, in order for the <filename>/etc/init.d/quagga</filename> script
    to invoke the daemon.</para>

    <para>The configuration of each of these daemons requires knowledge of
    the routing protocol in question. These protocols cannot be described
    in detail here, but the <emphasis role="pkg">quagga-doc</emphasis>
    provides ample explanation in the form of an <command>info</command>
    file. The same contents may be more easily browsed as HTML on the
    Quagga website: <ulink type="block"
    url="http://www.quagga.net/docs/docs-info.php"/> In addition, the
    syntax is very close to a standard router's configuration interface,
    and network administrators will adapt quickly to
    <command>quagga</command>.</para>

    <sidebar>
      <title><emphasis>IN PRACTICE</emphasis> OPSF, BGP or RIP?</title>

      <para>OSPF is generally the best protocol to use for dynamic routing
      on private networks, but BGP is more common for Internet-wide
      routing. RIP is rather ancient, and hardly used anymore.</para>
    </sidebar>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.ipv6">
    <title>IPv6</title>

    <para>IPv6, successor to IPv4, is a new version of the IP protocol
    designed to fix its flaws, most notably the scarcity of available IP
    addresses. This protocol handles the network layer; its purpose is to
    provide a way to address machines, to convey data to their intended
    destination, and to handle data fragmentation if needed (in other
    words, to split packets into chunks with a size that depends on the
    network links to be used on the path and to reassemble the chunks in
    their proper order on arrival).</para>

    <para>Debian kernels include IPv6 handling in the core kernel (which
    was not always the case; the <literal>ipv6</literal> module used to be
    optional). Basic tools such as <command>ping</command> and
    <command>traceroute</command> have their IPv6 equivalents in
    <command>ping6</command> and <command>traceroute6</command>, available
    respectively in the <emphasis role="pkg">iputils-ping</emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="pkg">iputils-tracepath</emphasis> packages.</para>
    <indexterm><primary>IPv6</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">iputils-ping</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">iputils-tracepath</emphasis></primary></indexterm>

    <para>The IPv6 network is configured similarly to IPv4, in
    <filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename>. But if you want that
    network to be globally available, you must ensure that you have an
    IPv6-capable router relaying traffic to the global IPv6 network.</para>

    <example id="example.network-interfaces-ipv6">
      <title>Example of IPv6 configuration</title>

      <programlisting>
iface eth0 inet6 static
    address 2001:db8:1234:5::1:1
    netmask 64
    # Disabling auto-configuration
    # up echo 0 &gt;/proc/sys/net/ipv6/conf/all/autoconf
    # The router is auto-configured and has no fixed address
    # (/proc/sys/net/ipv6/conf/all/accept_ra). If it had:
    # gateway 2001:db8:1234:5::1
</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>If a native IPv6 connection is not available, the fallback method
    is to use a tunnel over IPv4. Freenet6 is one (free) provider of such
    tunnels: <ulink type="block" url="http://www.freenet6.net/"/></para>
    <indexterm><primary>Freenet6</primary></indexterm>

    <para>To use a Freenet6 tunnel, you need to register on the website,
    then install the <emphasis role="pkg">tspc</emphasis> package and
    configure the tunnel. This requires editing the
    <filename>/etc/tsp/tspc.conf</filename> file: <literal>userid</literal>
    and <literal>password</literal> lines received by e-mail should be
    added, and <literal>server</literal> should be replaced with
    <literal>broker.freenet6.net</literal>.</para>

    <para>IPv6 connectivity is proposed to all machines on a local network
    by adding the three following directives to the
    <filename>/etc/tsp/tspc.conf</filename> file (assuming the local
    network is connected to the eth0 interface):</para>

    <programlisting>
host_type=router
prefix_len=48
if_prefix=eth0
</programlisting>

    <para>The machine then becomes the access router for a subnet with a
    48-bit prefix. Once the tunnel is aware of this change, the local
    network must be told about it; this implies installing the
    <command>radvd</command> daemon (from the similarly-named package).
    This IPv6 configuration daemon has a role similar to
    <command>dhcpd</command> in the IPv4 world.</para>

    <para>The <filename>/etc/radvd.conf</filename> configuration file must
    then be created (see
    <filename>/usr/share/doc/radvd/examples/simple-radvd.conf</filename> as
    a starting point). In our case, the only required change is the prefix,
    which needs to be replaced with the one provided by Freenet6; it can be
    found in the output of the <command>ifconfig</command> command, in the
    block concerning the <literal>tun</literal> interface.</para>
    <indexterm><primary><command>radvd</command></primary></indexterm>

    <para>Then run <command>/etc/init.d/tspc restart</command> and
    <command>/etc/init.d/radvd start</command>, and the IPv6 network should
    work.</para>

    <sidebar role="fil">
      <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> Programs built with IPv6</title>

      <para>Many pieces of software need to be adapted to handle IPv6. Most
      of the packages in Debian <emphasis
      role="distribution">Squeeze</emphasis> have been adapted already, but
      not all. A few volunteers had previously created a package archive
      dedicated to software specially rebuilt for IPv6; this archive was
      decommissioned in March 2007, both for lack of time and for lack of
      interest (since most of the patches have been integrated into the
      official packages). If your favorite package does not work with IPv6
      yet, help can be found on the <emphasis>debian-ipv6</emphasis>
      mailing-list. <ulink type="block"
      url="http://lists.debian.org/debian-ipv6/"/></para>
    </sidebar>

    <sidebar>
      <title><emphasis>CAUTION</emphasis> IPv6 and firewalls</title>
      <indexterm><primary>IPv6 firewall</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>firewall</primary><secondary>IPv6</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><command>ip6tables</command></primary></indexterm>

      <para>IPv6 tunneling over IPv4 (as opposed to native IPv6) requires the
      firewall to accept the traffic, which uses IPv4 protocol number 41.
      IPv6 connections can be restricted, in the same fashion as for IPv4:
      the standard Debian kernels include an adaptation of
      <emphasis>netfilter</emphasis> for IPv6. This IPv6-enabled
      <emphasis>netfilter</emphasis> is configured in a similar fashion to
      its IPv4 counterpart, except the program to use is
      <command>ip6tables</command> instead of
      <command>iptables</command>.</para>
    </sidebar>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.domain-name-servers">
    <title>Domain Name Servers (DNS)</title>
    <section id="section.dns-principe">
      <title>Principle and Mechanism</title>
      <indexterm><primary>DNS</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>server</primary><secondary>name</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>The <emphasis>Domain Name Service</emphasis> (DNS) is a
      fundamental component of the Internet: it maps host names to IP
      addresses (and vice-versa), which allows the use of
      <literal>www.debian.org</literal> instead of
      <literal>82.195.75.97</literal>.</para>

      <para>DNS records are organized in zones; each zone matches either a
      domain (or a subdomain) or an IP address range (since IP addresses
      are generally allocated in consecutive ranges). A primary server is
      authoritative on the contents of a zone; secondary servers, usually
      hosted on separate machines, provide regularly refreshed copies of
      the primary zone.</para>
      <indexterm><primary>zone</primary><secondary>DNS</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>DNS</primary><secondary>zone</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>Each zone can contain records of various kinds
      (<emphasis>Resource Records</emphasis>):</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>A</literal>: IPv4 address. <indexterm><primary>A,
	  DNS record</primary></indexterm></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>CNAME</literal>: alias (<emphasis>canonical
	  name</emphasis>). <indexterm><primary>CNAME, DNS
	  record</primary></indexterm></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>MX</literal>: <emphasis>mail exchange</emphasis>,
	  an email server. This information is used by other email servers
	  to find where to send email addressed to a given address. Each MX
	  record has a priority. The highest-priority server (with the
	  lowest number) is tried first (see sidebar <xref
	  linkend="sidebar.smtp"/>); other servers are contacted in order
	  of decreasing priority if the first one does not reply.
	  <indexterm><primary>MX</primary><secondary>DNS
	  record</secondary></indexterm></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>PTR</literal>: mapping of an IP address to a name.
	  Such a record is stored in a “reverse DNS” zone named after
	  the IP address range. For example,
	  <literal>1.168.192.in-addr.arpa</literal> is the zone containing
	  the reverse mapping for all addresses in the
	  <literal>192.168.1.0/24</literal> range. <indexterm><primary>PTR,
	  DNS record</primary></indexterm></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>AAAA</literal>: IPv6 address.
	  <indexterm><primary>AAAA, DNS record</primary></indexterm></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>NS</literal>: maps a name to a name server. Each
	  domain must have at least one NS record. These records point at a
	  DNS server that can answer queries concerning this domain; they
	  usually point at the primary and secondary servers for the
	  domain. These records also allow DNS delegation; for instance,
	  the <literal>falcot.com</literal> zone can include an NS record
	  for <literal>internal.falcot.com</literal>, which means that the
	  <literal>internal.falcot.com</literal> zone is handled by another
	  server. Of course, this server must declare an
	  <literal>internal.falcot.com</literal> zone.
	  <indexterm><primary>NS, DNS record</primary></indexterm></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

     
      <para><indexterm><primary>record</primary><secondary>DNS</secondary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>DNS record</primary></indexterm></para>

      <para>The reference name server, Bind, was developed and is
      maintained by ISC (<emphasis>Internet Software
      Consortium</emphasis>). It is provided in Debian by the <emphasis
      role="pkg">bind9</emphasis> package. Version 9 brings two major
      changes compared to previous versions. First, the DNS server can now
      run under an unprivileged user, so that a security vulnerability in
      the server does not grant root privileges to the attacker (as was
      seen repeatedly with versions 8.x).</para>

      <para>Furthermore, Bind supports the DNSSEC standard for signing (and
      therefore authenticating) DNS records, which allows blocking any
      spoofing of this data during man-in-the-middle attacks.</para>
      <indexterm><primary><emphasis role="pkg">bind9</emphasis></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>ISC</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>Internet Software Consortium</primary></indexterm>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>CULTURE</emphasis> DNSSEC</title>
        <indexterm><primary>DNSSEC</primary></indexterm>

	<para>The DNSSEC norm is quite complex; this partly explains why
	it's not in widespread usage yet (even if it perfectly coexists
	with DNS servers unaware of DNSSEC). To understand all the ins and
	outs, you should check the following article. <ulink type="block"
	url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_Name_System_Security_Extensions"/></para>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
    <section id="section.dns-config">
      <title>Configuring</title>

      <para>Configuration files for <command>bind</command>, irrespective
      of version, have the same structure.</para>

      <para>The Falcot administrators created a primary
      <literal>falcot.com</literal> zone to store information related to
      this domain, and a <literal>168.192.in-addr.arpa</literal> zone for
      reverse mapping of IP addresses in the local networks.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>CAUTION</emphasis> Names of reverse zones</title>
        <indexterm><primary>zone</primary><secondary>reverse</secondary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary>reverse zone</primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary><literal>in-addr.arpa</literal></primary></indexterm>

	<para>Reverse zones have a particular name. The zone covering the
	<literal>192.168.0.0/16</literal> network need to be named
	<literal>168.192.in-addr.arpa</literal>: the IP address components
	are reversed, and followed by the <emphasis>in-addr.arpa</emphasis>
	suffix.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <sidebar role="fil">
        <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> Testing the DNS server</title>

	<para>The <command>host</command> command (in the <emphasis
	role="pkg">bind9-host</emphasis> package) queries a DNS server, and
	can be used to test the server configuration. For example,
	<command>host machine.falcot.com localhost</command> checks the
	local server's reply for the <literal>machine.falcot.com</literal>
	query. The <command>host <replaceable>ipaddress</replaceable>
	localhost</command> tests the reverse resolution.</para>
        <indexterm><primary><command>host</command></primary></indexterm>
      </sidebar>

      <para>The following configuration excerpts, taken from the Falcot
      files, can serve as starting points to configure a DNS server:</para>
      <indexterm><primary><filename>named.conf</filename></primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary><filename>/etc/bind/named.conf</filename></primary></indexterm>

      <example id="example.bind-named.conf.local">
        <title>Excerpt of <filename>/etc/bind/named.conf.local</filename></title>

        <programlisting>
zone "falcot.com" {
        type master;
        file "/etc/bind/db.falcot.com";
        allow-query { any; };
        allow-transfer {
                195.20.105.149/32 ; // ns0.xname.org
                193.23.158.13/32 ; // ns1.xname.org
        };
};

zone "internal.falcot.com" {
        type master;
        file "/etc/bind/db.internal.falcot.com";
        allow-query { 192.168.0.0/16; };
};

zone "168.192.in-addr.arpa" {
        type master;
        file "/etc/bind/db.192.168";
        allow-query { 192.168.0.0/16; };
};
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <example id="example.bind-db.falcot.com">
        <title>Excerpt of <filename>/etc/bind/db.falcot.com</filename></title>

        <programlisting>; falcot.com Zone 
; admin.falcot.com. =&gt; zone contact: admin@falcot.com
$TTL    604800
@       IN      SOA     falcot.com. admin.falcot.com. (
                        20040121        ; Serial
                         604800         ; Refresh
                          86400         ; Retry
                        2419200         ; Expire
                         604800 )       ; Negative Cache TTL
;
; The @ refers to the zone name ("falcot.com" here)
; or to $ORIGIN if that directive has been used
;
@       IN      NS      ns
@       IN      NS      ns0.xname.org.

interne IN      NS      192.168.0.2

@       IN      A       212.94.201.10
@       IN      MX      5 mail
@       IN      MX      10 mail2

ns      IN      A       212.94.201.10
mail    IN      A       212.94.201.10
mail2   IN      A       212.94.201.11
www     IN      A       212.94.201.11

dns     IN      CNAME   ns
</programlisting>
      </example>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>CAUTION</emphasis> Syntax of a name</title>

	<para>The syntax of machine names follows strict rules. For
	instance, <literal>machine</literal> implies
	<literal>machine.<replaceable>domain</replaceable></literal>. If
	the domain name should not be appended to a name, said name must be
	written as <literal>machine.</literal> (with a dot as suffix).
	Indicating a DNS name outside the current domain therefore requires
	a syntax such as <literal>machine.otherdomain.com.</literal> (with
	the final dot).</para>
      </sidebar>

      <example id="example.bind-db.192.168">
        <title>Excerpt of <filename>/etc/bind/db.192.168</filename></title>

        <programlisting>; Reverse zone for 192.168.0.0/16
; admin.falcot.com. =&gt; zone contact: admin@falcot.com
$TTL    604800
@       IN      SOA     ns.interne.falcot.com. admin.falcot.com. (
                        20040121        ; Serial
                         604800         ; Refresh
                          86400         ; Retry
                        2419200         ; Expire
                         604800 )       ; Negative Cache TTL

        IN      NS      ns.interne.falcot.com.

; 192.168.0.1 -&gt; arrakis
1.0     IN      PTR     arrakis.interne.falcot.com.
; 192.168.0.2 -&gt; neptune
2.0     IN      PTR     neptune.interne.falcot.com.

; 192.168.3.1 -&gt; pau
1.3     IN      PTR     pau.interne.falcot.com.
</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.dhcp">
    <title>DHCP</title>
    <section id="section.dhcp-presentation">
      <title>Presentation</title>

      <para>DHCP (for <emphasis>Dynamic Host Configuration
      Protocol</emphasis>) is a protocol by which a machine can
      automatically get its network configuration when it boots. This
      allows centralizing the management of network configurations, and
      ensuring that all desktop machines get similar settings.</para>
      <indexterm><primary>DHCP</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm><primary>network</primary><secondary>DHCP configuration</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>A DHCP server provides many network-related parameters. The
      most common of these is an IP address and the network where the
      machine belongs, but it can also provide other information, such as
      DNS servers, WINS servers, NTP servers, and so on.</para>

      <para>The Internet Software Consortium (also involved in developing
      <command>bind</command>) is the main author of the DHCP server. The
      matching Debian package is <emphasis
      role="pkg">isc-dhcp-server</emphasis>.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="section.dhcp-config">
      <title>Configuring</title>

      <para>The first elements that need to be edited in the DHCP server
      configuration file (<filename>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</filename>) are
      the domain name and the DNS servers. If this server is alone on the
      local network (as defined by the broadcast propagation), the
      <literal>authoritative</literal> directive must also be enabled (or
      uncommented). One also needs to create a <literal>subnet</literal>
      section describing the local network and the configuration
      information to be provided. The following example fits a
      <literal>192.168.0.0/24</literal> local network with a router at
      <literal>192.168.0.1</literal> serving as the gateway. Available IP
      addresses are in the range <literal>192.168.0.128</literal> to
      <literal>192.168.0.254</literal>.</para>

      <example id="example.dhcp-dhcpd.conf">
        <title>Excerpt of <filename>/etc/dhcp/dhcpd.conf</filename></title>

        <programlisting>
#
# Sample configuration file for ISC dhcpd for Debian
#

# The ddns-updates-style parameter controls whether or not the server will
# attempt to do a DNS update when a lease is confirmed. We default to the
# behavior of the version 2 packages ('none', since DHCP v2 didn't
# have support for DDNS.)
ddns-update-style interim;

# option definitions common to all supported networks...
option domain-name "internal.falcot.com";
option domain-name-servers ns.internal.falcot.com;

default-lease-time 600;
max-lease-time 7200;

# If this DHCP server is the official DHCP server for the local
# network, the authoritative directive should be uncommented.
authoritative;

# Use this to send dhcp log messages to a different log file (you also
# have to hack syslog.conf to complete the redirection).
log-facility local7;

# My subnet
subnet 192.168.0.0 netmask 255.255.255.0 {
    option routers 192.168.0.1;
    option broadcast-address 192.168.0.255;
    range 192.168.0.128 192.168.0.254;
    ddns-domainname "internal.falcot.com";
}
</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
    <section id="section.dhcp-dns">
      <title>DHCP and DNS</title>
      <indexterm><primary>DNS</primary><secondary>automated updates</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>A nice feature is the automated registering of DHCP clients in
      the DNS zone, so that each machine gets a significant name (rather
      than something impersonal such as
      <literal>machine-192-168-0-131.internal.falcot.com</literal>). Using
      this feature requires configuring the DNS server to accept updates to
      the <literal>internal.falcot.com</literal> DNS zone from the DHCP
      server, and configuring the latter to submit updates for each
      registration.</para>

      <para>In the <command>bind</command> case, the
      <literal>allow-update</literal> directive needs to be added to each
      of the zones that the DHCP server is to edit (the one for the
      <literal>internal.falcot.com</literal> domain, and the reverse zone).
      This directive lists the IP addresses allowed to perform these
      updates; it should therefore contain the possible addresses of the
      DHCP server (both the local address and the public address, if
      appropriate).</para>

      <programlisting>
allow-update { 127.0.0.1 192.168.0.1 212.94.201.10 !any };
</programlisting>

      <para>Beware! A zone that can be modified <emphasis>will</emphasis>
      be changed by <command>bind</command>, and the latter will overwrite
      its configuration files at regular intervals. Since this automated
      procedure produces files that are less human-readable than
      manually-written ones, the Falcot administrators handle the
      <literal>internal.falcot.com</literal> domain with a delegated DNS
      server; this means the <literal>falcot.com</literal> zone file stays
      firmly under their manual control.</para>

      <para>The DHCP server configuration excerpt above already includes
      the directives required for DNS zone updates: they are the
      <literal>ddns-update-style interim;</literal> and
      <literal>ddns-domain-name "internal.falcot.com";</literal> lines in
      the block describing the subnet.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="sect.network-diagnosis-tools">
    <title>Network Diagnosis Tools</title>

    <para>When a network application does not run as expected, it is
    important to be able to look under the hood. Even when everything seems
    to run smoothly, running a network diagnosis can help ensure everything
    is working as it should. Several diagnosis tools exists for this
    purpose; each one operates on a different level.</para>
    <section id="section.netstat">
      <title>Local Diagnosis: <command>netstat</command></title>
      <indexterm><primary><command>netstat</command></primary></indexterm>

      <para>Let's first mention the <command>netstat</command> command (in
      the <emphasis role="pkg">net-tools</emphasis> package); it displays
      an instant summary of a machine's network activity. When invoked with
      no argument, this command lists all open connections; this list can
      be very verbose since it includes many Unix-domain sockets (widely
      used by daemons) which do not involve the network at all (for
      example, <literal>dbus</literal> communication,
      <literal>X11</literal> traffic, and communications between virtual
      filesystems and the desktop).</para>

      <para>Common invocations therefore use options that alter
      <command>netstat</command>'s behavior. The most frequently used
      options include:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>-t</literal>, which filters the results to only
	  include TCP connections;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>-u</literal>, which works similarly for UDP
	  connections; these options are not mutually exclusive, and one of
	  them is enough to stop displaying Unix-domain connections;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>-a</literal>, to also list listening sockets
	  (waiting for incoming connections);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>-n</literal>, to display the results numerically:
	  IP addresses (no DNS resolution), port numbers (no aliases as
	  defined in <filename>/etc/services</filename>) and user ids (no
	  login names);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>-p</literal>, to list the processes involved; this
	  option is only useful when <command>netstat</command> is run as
	  root, since normal users will only see their own
	  processes;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
	  <para><literal>-c</literal>, to continuously refresh the list of
	  connections.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Other options, documented in the
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>netstat</refentrytitle>
      <manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> manual page, provide an even
      finer control over the displayed results. In practice, the first five
      options are so often used together that systems and network
      administrators practically acquired <command>netstat -tupan</command>
      as a reflex. Typical results, on a lightly loaded machine, may look
      like the following:</para>

      <screen role="scale">
<computeroutput># </computeroutput><userinput>netstat -tupan</userinput>
<computeroutput>Active Internet connections (servers and established)
Proto Recv-Q Send-Q Local Address           Foreign Address         State       PID/Program name
tcp        0      0 0.0.0.0:22              0.0.0.0:*               LISTEN      2224/sshd       
tcp        0      0 127.0.0.1:25            0.0.0.0:*               LISTEN      994/exim4       
tcp        0      0 192.168.1.241:22        192.168.1.128:47372     ESTABLISHED 2944/sshd: roland [
tcp        0      0 192.168.1.241:22        192.168.1.128:32970     ESTABLISHED 2232/sshd: roland [
tcp6       0      0 :::22                   :::*                    LISTEN      2224/sshd       
tcp6       0      0 ::1:25                  :::*                    LISTEN      994/exim4       
udp        0      0 0.0.0.0:68              0.0.0.0:*                           633/dhclient    
udp        0      0 192.168.1.241:123       0.0.0.0:*                           764/ntpd        
udp        0      0 127.0.0.1:123           0.0.0.0:*                           764/ntpd        
udp        0      0 0.0.0.0:123             0.0.0.0:*                           764/ntpd        
udp6       0      0 fe80::a00:27ff:fe6c:123 :::*                                764/ntpd        
udp6       0      0 2002:52e0:87e4:0:a0:123 :::*                                764/ntpd        
udp6       0      0 ::1:123                 :::*                                764/ntpd        
udp6       0      0 :::123                  :::*                                764/ntpd        
</computeroutput></screen>

      <para>As expected, this lists established connections, two SSH
      connections in this case, and applications waiting for incoming
      connections (listed as <literal>LISTEN</literal>), notably the Exim4
      email server listening on port 25.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="section.nmap">
      <title>Remote Diagnosis: <command>nmap</command></title>
      <indexterm><primary><command>nmap</command></primary></indexterm>

      <para><command>nmap</command> (in the similarly-named package) is, in
      a way, the remote equivalent for <command>netstat</command>. It can
      scan a set of “well-known” ports for one or several remote
      servers, and list the ports where an application is found to answer
      to incoming connections. Furthermore, <command>nmap</command> is able
      to identify some of these applications, sometimes even their version
      number. The counterpart of this tool is that, since it runs remotely,
      it cannot provide information on processes or users; however, it can
      operate on several targets at once.</para>

      <para>A typical <command>nmap</command> invocation only uses the
      <literal>-A</literal> option (so that <command>nmap</command>
      attempts to identify the versions of the server software it finds)
      followed by one or more IP addresses or DNS names of machines to
      scan. Again, many more options exist to finely control the behavior
      of <command>nmap</command>; please refer to the documentation in the
      <citerefentry> <refentrytitle>nmap</refentrytitle>
      <manvolnum>1</manvolnum> </citerefentry> manual page.</para>

      <screen width="80" role="scale">
<computeroutput># </computeroutput><userinput>nmap scouzmir</userinput>
<computeroutput>
Starting Nmap 5.00 ( http://nmap.org ) at 2010-10-12 18:52 CEST
Interesting ports on 192.168.1.101:
Not shown: 998 closed ports
PORT    STATE SERVICE
22/tcp  open  ssh
111/tcp open  rpcbind
MAC Address: 52:54:00:99:01:01 (QEMU Virtual NIC)

Nmap done: 1 IP address (1 host up) scanned in 2.11 seconds
# </computeroutput><userinput>nmap -A localhost</userinput>
<computeroutput>
Starting Nmap 5.00 ( http://nmap.org ) at 2010-10-12 18:59 CEST
Warning: Hostname localhost resolves to 2 IPs. Using 127.0.0.1.
Interesting ports on localhost (127.0.0.1):
Not shown: 997 closed ports
PORT    STATE SERVICE VERSION
22/tcp  open  ssh     OpenSSH 5.5p1 Debian 4 (protocol 2.0)
|  ssh-hostkey: 1024 af:07:60:17:16:64:6f:ee:c4:ca:b5:64:1e:4a:4c:22 (DSA)
|_ 2048 25:b0:aa:6b:11:5a:56:b6:8d:2d:ed:b3:16:17:96:33 (RSA)
25/tcp  open  smtp    Exim smtpd 4.72
|  smtp-commands: EHLO scouzmir.internal.placard.fr.eu.org Hello localhost [127.0.0.1], SIZE 52428800, PIPELINING, HELP
|_ HELP Commands supported: AUTH HELO EHLO MAIL RCPT DATA NOOP QUIT RSET HELP
111/tcp open  rpcbind
|  rpcinfo:  
|  100000  2    111/udp  rpcbind  
|  100024  1  53273/udp  status   
|  100000  2    111/tcp  rpcbind  
|_ 100024  1  41127/tcp  status   
No exact OS matches for host (If you know what OS is running on it, see http://nmap.org/submit/ ).
TCP/IP fingerprint:
OS:SCAN(V=5.00%D=10/12%OT=22%CT=1%CU=34421%PV=N%DS=0%G=Y%TM=4CB4941A%P=i686
OS:-pc-linux-gnu)SEQ(SP=BF%GCD=1%ISR=CC%TI=Z%CI=Z%II=I%TS=8)OPS(O1=M400CST1
OS:1NW4%O2=M400CST11NW4%O3=M400CNNT11NW4%O4=M400CST11NW4%O5=M400CST11NW4%O6
OS:=M400CST11)WIN(W1=8000%W2=8000%W3=8000%W4=8000%W5=8000%W6=8000)ECN(R=Y%D
OS:F=Y%T=40%W=8018%O=M400CNNSNW4%CC=Y%Q=)T1(R=Y%DF=Y%T=40%S=O%A=S+%F=AS%RD=
OS:0%Q=)T2(R=N)T3(R=Y%DF=Y%T=40%W=8000%S=O%A=S+%F=AS%O=M400CST11NW4%RD=0%Q=
OS:)T4(R=Y%DF=Y%T=40%W=0%S=A%A=Z%F=R%O=%RD=0%Q=)T5(R=Y%DF=Y%T=40%W=0%S=Z%A=
OS:S+%F=AR%O=%RD=0%Q=)T6(R=Y%DF=Y%T=40%W=0%S=A%A=Z%F=R%O=%RD=0%Q=)T7(R=Y%DF
OS:=Y%T=40%W=0%S=Z%A=S+%F=AR%O=%RD=0%Q=)U1(R=Y%DF=N%T=40%IPL=164%UN=0%RIPL=
OS:G%RID=G%RIPCK=G%RUCK=G%RUD=G)IE(R=Y%DFI=N%T=40%CD=S)

Network Distance: 0 hops
Service Info: Host: scouzmir.internal.placard.fr.eu.org; OS: Linux

OS and Service detection performed. Please report any incorrect results at http://nmap.org/submit/ .
Nmap done: 1 IP address (1 host up) scanned in 21.32 seconds
</computeroutput>
</screen>

      <para>As expected, the SSH and Exim4 applications are listed. Note
      that not all applications listen on all IP addresses; since Exim4 is
      only accessible on the <literal>lo</literal> loopback interface, it
      only appears during an analysis of <literal>localhost</literal> and
      not when scanning <literal>scouzmir</literal> (which maps to the
      <literal>eth0</literal> interface on the same machine).</para>
    </section>
    <section id="section.sniffers">
      <title>Sniffers: <command>tcpdump</command> and <command>wireshark</command></title>

      <para>Sometimes, one needs to look at what actually goes on the wire,
      packet by packet. These cases call for a “frame analyzer”, more
      widely known as a <emphasis>sniffer</emphasis>. Such a tool observes
      all the packets that reach a given network interface, and displays
      them in a user-friendly way.</para>
      <indexterm><primary><command>tcpdump</command></primary></indexterm>

      <para>The venerable tool in this domain is
      <command>tcpdump</command>, available as a standard tool on a wide
      range of platforms. It allows many kinds of network traffic capture,
      but the representation of this traffic stays rather obscure. We will
      therefore not describe it in further detail.</para>
      <indexterm><primary><command>wireshark</command></primary></indexterm>

      <para>A more recent (and more modern) tool,
      <command>wireshark</command> (in the <emphasis
      role="pkg">wireshark</emphasis> package), is slowly becoming the new
      reference in network traffic analysis due to its many decoding
      modules that allow for a simplified analysis of the captured packets.
      The packets are displayed graphically with an organization based on
      the protocol layers. This allows a user to visualize all protocols
      involved in a packet. For example, given a packet containing an HTTP
      request, <command>wireshark</command> displays, separately, the
      information concerning the physical layer, the Ethernet layer, the IP
      packet information, the TCP connection parameters, and finally the
      HTTP request itself.</para>

      <figure id="figure.wireshark">
        <title>The <command>wireshark</command> network traffic analyzer</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/wireshark.png" scalefit="1" width="75%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>In our example, the packets traveling over SSH are filtered
      out (with the <literal>!tcp.port == 22</literal> filter). The packet
      currently displayed was developed at the TCP and HTTP layers.</para>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>TIP</emphasis> <command>wireshark</command> with no graphical interface: <command>tshark</command></title>
        <indexterm><primary><command>tshark</command></primary></indexterm>

	<para>When one cannot run a graphical interface, or does not wish
	to do so for whatever reason, a text-only version of
	<command>wireshark</command> also exists under the name
	<command>tshark</command> (in a separate <emphasis
	role="pkg">tshark</emphasis> package). Most of the capture and
	decoding features are still available, but the lack of a graphical
	interface necessarily limits the interactions with the program
	(filtering packets after they've been captured, tracking of a given
	TCP connection, and so on). It can still be used as a first
	approach. If further manipulations are intended and require the
	graphical interface, the packets can be saved to a file and this
	file can be loaded into a graphical <command>wireshark</command>
	running on another machine.</para>
      </sidebar>

      <sidebar>
        <title><emphasis>CULTURE</emphasis> <command>ethereal</command> and <command>wireshark</command></title>
        <indexterm><primary><command>ethereal</command></primary></indexterm>
        <indexterm><primary><command>tethereal</command></primary></indexterm>

	<para><command>wireshark</command> seems to be relatively young;
	however, it is only the new name for a software application
	previously known as <command>ethereal</command>. When its main
	developer left the company where he was employed, he was not able
	to arrange for the transfer of the registered trademark. As an
	alternative he went for a name change; only the name and the icons
	for the software actually changed.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
